Feelings are Suffering

[source]

How should one free oneself from suffering?

The very first step that one should make is to learn how not to crave the cessation of suffering. At first glance this might seem simple, but actually it is not so straightforward at all; for we cannot assume that an untrained, ordinary person even knows what truly suffering is.

In order to know dukkha it is not enough just to suffer. To know dukkha, one has to recognize, within the present experience, what is and what is not necessary. The point is that, in the experience of pain, certain aspects are inevitable, while others, are not. In different words – the ‘painfulness’ of pain is suffering and not the pain itself.

Let me get back to the opening statement that one should not crave the cessation of suffering; why is that essential? The immediate reason of our suffering, as the Buddha tells us, is our craving or taṇha. It is because of taṇha that our experience of pain is painful. This applies to the other two kinds of feeling too. Thus, we can say, that it is because of craving that feelings are dukkha. In the first type, unpleasant feeling, craving for the cessation of that feeling causes one to suffer: the painful feeling is present there, directly opposed to one’s desire for it to not-be, to disappear. In this way a discrepancy is created, a discrepancy which is nothing but dukkha. In the second type, pleasant feeling, craving for more of that feeling is manifested, thus the actual pleasant feeling appears as unpleasant, when attended from the direction of that increased pleasure which is craved for. The present feeling of pleasure becomes inadequate, a lack which needs to be satisfied. Again, the discrepancy arises, which one tries to overcome by a further pursuit of various things in the world which, will intensify his pleasure further. One hopes that such attempt will ‘fill the gap’ within, but needless to say, that is impossible since the discrepancy is actually being constantly generated by the presence of taṇha, and not by the various objects in the world.

“Thought and lust are a man’s sensuality,
Not the various things in the world;
Thought and lust are a man’s sensuality,
The various things just stand there in the world;
But the wise get rid of desire therein.”

– AN VI 63 / iii, 411

When it comes to third type, neither-pleasant-nor-unpleasant feelings (i.e. neutral), suffering is experienced as a result of one craving for feelings themselves, since neutral feeling is not recognized at all:

“Neutral feeling is pleasant when known [as such],
and unpleasant when not-known [as such]”

– MN 44 / i, 303

So, to summarize, one’s experience of pain is not the reason for one’s suffering. It is rather the presence of craving, in one’s experience, that suffering is there. As long as this remains the case, one will be a “victim” of one’s own feelings, be they pleasant, unpleasant or neutral.

Existence Means Control

[source]

In order for something to exist (bhava), in order for it to be, in a full and appropriated sense, that thing has to be given first, in the form of an experience as a whole. When I say ‘given’, this should be understood in the sense that we can only “find” things as already being there, in the world. (Cf. Sartre’s statement in Being & Nothingness that every thing comes with past). The fact is that things can only be found when they are attended to and this means that – fundamentally speaking – they are beyond one’s control[1]: one is not their creator. Thus, one’s experience as a whole cannot be controlled; the most a person can do is to modify an already given state of affairs, on a more particular level.

Take the five-aggregates as an example: their nature is to appear, disappear, and change while standing, at their own accord. It is only with upādāna that this characteristic is obscured[2], and in such cases the apparent Self becomes the fundamental agent of the process instead, or at least this is how it appears to a puthujjana. One who is not free from upādāna, and the Self-view, confuses the fact that the five-aggregates (or in this case the five-holding-aggregates) can be modified or affected once they arise, with the notion that they are controlled. This notion of control also supports (or feeds) the view that ‘Self’ is their creator, which in return feeds that notion, and so on indefinitely. This is why with ‘Self’ there comes the perception of mastery over one’s experience – “Attā, ‘self’, is fundamentally a notion of mastery over things.” (Ñāṇavīra Thera, Notes on Dhamma, DHAMMA)

The Self then, as a “master”, appears as something different, something apart from the five-holding-aggregates. Furthermore, the Self keeps finding proof for its existence by constantly interfering and modifying (when possible) the arisen states of the five-holding-aggregates. The Self finds pleasure in doing so.

On the other hand, if the Self would see that, despite all of the proof, its mastery actually requires (or directly depends upon) the five-aggregates, the notion of control would cease[3]. It becomes clear that ‘Self’ cannot possibly exercise any fundamental control over their appearing, disappearing, and change while standing. This is why by contemplating this long enough, one can become an arahat:

“Then, monks, at another time the Buddha Vipassī dwelt contemplating the appearing and disappearing of the five-holding-aggregates… And as he remained contemplating the appearing and disappearing of the five-holding-aggregates, before long his mind was freed from the fetters without remainder.”

– Mahāpadāna Sutta, DN 14 / ii, 35

Even if one can control them, first they have to be. In other words – the nature of control is seen as something beyond our control. [back]

As a matter of fact, it’s not only the characteristic that is obscured, the five-aggregates are not seen either, most of the time. [back]

For a puthujjana it is not enough to see this once. It is only with the repetition of this insight (achieved through effort), that the habitual view of control will disappear, and be replaced (gradually too) with the view of an inherent lack of control – the view of impermanence. When it is seen that impermanence underlies every project of the Self, the Self ceases to be Self, since without its mastery, selfhood cannot stand. (Cf. Ñāṇavīra Thera, Notes on Dhamma, PARAMATTHA SACCA, para. 6) [back]

With birth, Death applies

[source]

1. We are born. We come into this world through our birth. As we shall see in the following paragraphs, there are many ways that one can think of one’s birth. However, from a phenomenological point of view our birth is always here with us. The fact that one is constantly engaged with the world of one’s desires, decisions and miseries, means that one is born – his birth is present. Obviously, for someone not used to thinking phenomenologically, it might be fairly difficult to pull oneself out of the habitual way of regarding things as something which is clearly defined, something palpable in one’s experience. For such a person ‘birth’ is an event from the past, and we shall address this issue in the paragraphs to follow. However, there is also a simpler and easily overlooked reason for one failing to grasp the phenomenological description of ‘birth’. In our language the term ‘birth’, as a designation of experience, carries certain past connotations. These connotations are absolutely gratuitous, and we shall see that the reason for that lies in people’s views (diṭṭhi). The established usage of terminology draws its significance (i.e. the meaning of its words) from the most common views (on the level of humanity or a particular culture), about the nature of experience. Needless to say, the common views are rarely correct, especially when it comes to the experience of an individual. These views can never represent the real order of things. Thus, apart from the way we speak, and use the language, nothing requires us to think that birth can, and shall only be understood as a past event which has started and ended in time.

2. Naturally, it is possible for one to regard, and understand to a certain extent, birth as something which has happened to him a long time ago, even without having the actual memory of the event. However, this kind of limited understanding is only possible in the objective (scientific) view of the world, and oneself. We can even go a step further and say that it is precisely because of that view that one thinks of birth (and other things, including ageing-and-death) in these temporal categories. With this kind of view, the objective world in front of one, the world which is in time, takes precedence over one’s experience as such, which is of time (cf. Ñāṇavīra Thera, Notes on Dhamma, FUNDAMENTAL STRUCTURE, Dynamic Aspect, para. 5). One starts regarding the objects that appear through one’s experience, as something more fundamental than the experience itself – he puts second that which is to come first, and he puts first that which is to come second[1]. As a result of this one starts regarding oneself objectively as also being in time. Thus, time develops into a category which has become external to everything, and all of the things appear as being “within” it[2]. Therefore, one sees that others are born, their event of birth occurs in time, when he observes it externally. But because he views himself externally too, he naturally (i.e. in conformity with his view) comes to assume that his birth has also occurred some time ago in the past. One also assumes, since he can see it in his everyday experience, that death will happen to him in that same ‘external’ sense, “as it happens to others all the time”. By regarding things in this way, he, as an individual, does not feel threatened by any of it, until the actual death comes of course. So, we can see that one doesn’t adopt this objective view voluntarily – when avijjā is present, the view is developed naturally as the quickest way of offering one assurance from a threatening world. The world and one’s experience becomes explainable and measurable – one has regained control.

Let us get back to the phenomenon of ‘birth’, we were discussing. The Buddha referred to ‘birth’ as: “Whatever birth, taking birth, descent, coming-to-being, coming-forth, manifestation of aggregates, and acquisition of [sense] spheres of the various beings in this or that group of beings, that is called birth.” (Sammādiṭṭhi Sutta, M. 9/i 50)

Thus, although we can agree that birth is some sort of a “beginning”, so to speak, a “manifestation of the aggregates”, what obliges us to think that that beginning has ended there? The fact that one keeps accepting and using the five-aggregates, the fact that one is constantly involved with the world of one’s senses, doesn’t that mean that one’s manifestation of aggregates is present[3]? And would one be able to desire various things in the world, if those things were not manifested? If one were able to relinquish any attachment for his own body, would one be bothered when that body falls apart and dies? It is because one affirms that manifestation of the five-aggregates, through desire-and-lust for them, that the manifestation exists, it comes-into-being – with being, birth is (bhavapaccayā jāti). And when one regards it as ‘mine’, one ages, falls sick and dies (and also experiences any other misery possible in this life) – with birth, ageing-and-death (jātipaccayā jarāmaraṇaṃ…). If there is no being whatsoever, would manifestation be able to manifest itself? And if nothing manifested, would one be able to appropriate it? And if there is nothing which belongs to one, would one suffer on account of those things breaking up and disappearing? No, because one has escaped.

3. Let us go back to the question of when birth ends. Actually, we can even ask when does birth start? The common view is that first one is conceived, and than, after nine months or so, things culminate in one being born. But when does the conception take place or when exactly is one born? Is it with the formation of an embryo or with cutting of the umbilical cord? Generally, the accepted view is that birth is over when the baby comes out of the womb and into the world. And when it comes to ‘general views’, we all know that people often tend to blindly comply to them, taking them for granted for the most (or whole) of their lives, without even realizing they are doing so. In this case, ‘birth’ becomes that which accords to the majority of opinions on that subject. One chooses to conform with “what everyone else thinks”, since the majority is “always in the right”. One accepts Heidegger’s impersonal ‘They’ as a dictator of one’s own values, one finds safety in doing so. However, no matter how secure the majority’s view might seem, all it takes is for someone else to come along and say (perhaps supporting it with “the latest medical research”) that birth actually ends when the formation of an infant is completed in the womb, and that coming out of the mother is not relevant as such, to question of birth itself. (Though, for parents, even if they happen to be those scientists, this is probably the most relevant part[4].) If his utterance manages to change the general opinion, if the majority of people come to accept it, we will have a new, “more accurate” view on the nature of birth. The majority might have been wrong earlier, but now it is in the right… until it changes. And one can again choose to conform to that majority and make a choice out of it, but no matter how far one goes that choice will always remain personal, and as such, be on the level of an individual. So, although one thinks what everybody else does, one nevertheless remains responsible for that very thinking. It becomes clear then that by choosing the majority’s opinion on a certain subject (in this case ‘birth), out of ‘faith’ in modern science (or religion) perhaps, a person chooses his individual view on given subject. So, by deciding to accept the scientific explanation of birth, one decides that birth, for him, is something observable, an event in the world. Thus, whether one is aware of it or not, one is responsible for the meaning of things in one’s experience. Even if we go further and say that we could pinpoint the exact moment of birth[5], when, for example, conception takes place, and even if the whole of humanity, without an exception, agreed upon it, nevertheless, this would not escape the nature of ‘view’, and that is to be ‘imposed’ onto things in one’s experience, while at the same time directly depending upon them. In our case that would most likely be the ‘objective view’, which is of course, based on personal preferences and inclinations[6]. Thus, for a puthujjana coming-out-of-womb is that which is birth. His birth exists.

The Buddha, on the other hand, talks about the nature of birth, as a phenomena (dhamma), in one’s experience. He does not refer to birth as an occurrence in time, upon which even puthujjanas cannot agree, and this can be seen from the usual paṭiccasamuppāda (p.s.) description. In this description, jāti refers to that ‘nature’ of birth and any temporal events are completely irrelevant to it. If there is no ‘birth’ whatsoever, if there is no manifestation (as such) of the aggregates, a puthujjana would not be able to regard any event (in this case ‘coming-out-of-womb’) as his[7] birth[8]. Thus, one doesn’t suffer on account of birth as an event in the past, one suffers on account of the nature of birth in the present. In p.s. context, ‘birth’ structurally precedes ‘ageing-and-death’. ‘Ageing-and-death’ is not ‘birth’, but they wouldn’t be without it – together they arise, together they cease. So, it is that with ‘birth’, ‘ageing-and-death’ (and ‘sorrow, lamentation, pain, grief and despair’) apply. Consequently, if we were to discuss jāramaraṇaṃ, we could say that it is because ageing-and-death is present, that one will age and die (and suffer) in time. But, if one could manage, through an understanding of the Dhamma, to free oneself from ‘being’ – to bring it to an end – ‘ birth’ and ‘ageing-and-death’ would cease to exist for him: all of the temporal occasions for suffering would cease to be his suffering, since by not-being born, one doesn’t have the desire to interfere with them any more – one is free.

5. Let me just say something more, for those who find it difficult to accept that the existential (phenomenological) method[9] can validly be applied to Dhamma. We can put aside Sartre, Heidegger and those like them, and disregard what they have to say about birth. However, even in that case, still, we need look no further than the p.s. description in order to see what the Buddha meant by ‘birth’. In Sammādiṭṭhi Sutta, M. 9/i 50, it is said, as we already referred to it earlier on:

When a noble disciple has thus understood birth, the origin of birth, the cessation of birth, and the way leading to the cessation of birth… he here and now makes an end of suffering. In that way too a noble disciple is one of right view… and has arrived at this true Dhamma.

Thus, a Noble disciple, an ariyasāvaka, can by understanding ‘birth’, in the same sense that he would have understood the Four Noble Truths – directly and timelessly – free oneself and become an arahat. So, one may rightly ask now: would this be possible, if ‘birth’ were not already somehow present[10], as a phenomena, in our experience? How would one be able to understand birth directly and without involving time? If one’s birth was indeed a distant event, in some maternity ward perhaps, one’s fate would be sealed according to the Sammādiṭṭhi Sutta, since the event of birth has already passed and cannot possibly be understood directly. Fortunately, one’s birth is not in the past, so one can, if one chooses to follow the Buddha’s Teaching, cease to, in the present, regard ‘birth’ as his and by doing so remove himself from the domain of ageing-and-death, sorrow, lamentation, pain, grief and despair. One can escape.

Cf. Maurice Merleau-Ponty, in his Phenomenology of Perception, (Routledge Classics, 2007, p. 82): I detach myself from my experience and pass to the idea. Like the object, the idea purports to be the same for everybody, valid in all times and places, and the individuation of an object in an objective point of time and space finally appears as the expression of a universal positing power. I am no longer concerned with my body, nor with time, nor with the world, as I experience them in antepredicative knowledge, in the inner communion that I have with them. I now refer to my body only as a idea, to the universe as idea, to the idea of space and the idea of time. Thus ‘objective’ thought (in Kierkegaard’s sense) is formed – being that of common sense and of science – which finally causes us to lose contact with perceptual experience, of which it is nevertheless the outcome and the natural sequel. The whole life of consciousness is characterized by the tendency to posit objects, since it is consciousness, that is to say self-knowledge, only in so far as it takes hold of itself and draws itself together in an identifiable object. And yet the absolute positing of a single object is the death of consciousness, since it congeals the whole of existence, as a crystal placed in a solution suddenly crystallizes it. [back]

Time, as a phenomena in one’s experience, is regarded as more primordial (read – ‘permanent’), than the experience of things. The things seem to come and go, while the sense of time stays. [back]

Furthermore, nothing obliges us to think that ‘manifestation of aggregates’ refers to the event of coming-out-of-womb. The Buddha has said that “when mother and father come together and the mother is in season and the one to be tied is present, with the coming together of these three things, there is descent into the womb” (M. 38/i 265-66). Thus, the five-aggregates are already manifested, in a way, even at the stage of an embryo, and before the infant is formed. (Cf. also A.III, 61/i, 176-7) [back]

And therefore it is not accidental that this is most commonly regarded as birth. [back]

This, in itself, is clearly impossible, since the “exactness”, in any area of science, is determined by the capacities of one’s perception (i.e. the refinement of our technology and observational instruments). (Cf. Ñāṇavīra Thera, Notes on Dhamma, FUNDAMENTAL STRUCTURE, Static Aspect, para. 16.) [back]

It is very unlikely that the whole of humanity could actually agree on this (or anything), since all people are not the same. The birth of a baby, in this case, carries different significance for different individuals. A mother might say that her baby was born the moment she held it in her arms, and that it was conceived the moment she fell in love with its father. A scientist, in his carefully cultivated attitude of disinterestedness, might say that a baby is conceived when embryo cells become discernible (he observes it under his microscope!), and perhaps that it is born when it starts to breathe independently. For a doctor, involved in performing abortions, there is no question of ‘baby’ (i.e. ‘human’), until three months are due. Thus, it is how one feels towards ‘birth’, how one perceives it, how one intends it, that determines what that birth is for him. (“Contacted, monks, one feels; contacted, one intends; contacted, one perceives.” – Saḷāyatana Saṃyutta, iv,10.) Also, compare the passage from the Madhupiṇḍika Sutta, M. 18/i 111-112:

Dependent on the eye and forms (ear, nose…) eye consciousness arise. The meeting of three is contact. With contact as condition there is feeling. What man feels, that he perceives. What he perceives, that he thinks about. What he thinks about that he diversifies. With what he diversified as the source calculations about perceptions of diversification occupy a man with respect to past, future and present.

[back]

Compare this passage from J.P. Sartre – Existentialism is Humanism, chapter on ‘Freedom and Responsibility’: Yet I find an absolute responsibility for the fact that my facticity (here the fact of my birth) is directly inapprehensible and even inconceivable, for this fact of my birth never appears as a brute fact but always across a projective reconstruction of my for-itself. I am ashamed of being born or I rejoice over it, or in attempting to get rid of my life I affirm that I live and I assume this life as bad. Thus in a certain sense I choose to be born. This choice itself is integrally affected with facticity since I am not able not to choose, but this facticity in turn will appear only in so far as I surpass it toward my ends. Thus facticity is everywhere, but inapprehensible; I never encounter anything except my responsibility. That is why I can not ask, “Why was I born? “ or curse the day of my birth or declare that I did not ask to be born, for these various attitudes towards my birth – i.e., toward the fact that I realize a presence in the world – are absolutely nothing else but ways of assuming this birth in full responsibility and of making it mine. [back]

This can be stated even more precisely: the temporal things (events in time) are possible only because there is an atemporal structure (nature of time) – time is secondary to one’s experience. Hence, the p.s. is said to be akālika, ‘timeless’. (Cf. Ñāṇavīra Thera, Notes on Dhamma, NP. & FUNDAMENTAL STRUCTURE). That is why, in the Sammādiṭṭhi Sutta, M. 9, we can see that a Noble disciple can, by understanding ‘being’, ‘birth’ or ‘ageing-and-death’ respectively, come to the same result – complete freedom from suffering, arahatship. P.s. can be understood by understanding all or any of its “pairs”, since each of them represent, or rather are, the principle of simultaneous dependent origination – ‘when this, this is’ (imasmiṃ sati idaṃ hoti). [back]

We are not interested in the conclusions (or lack of them, as Ven. Ñāṇavīra would say) they drew from the method itself. [back]

Cf. Ñāṇavīra Thera, op. cit., NP., para. 9 & 10. This ‘somehow’ is important to note. If a puthujjana, who is not satisfied with the idea of birth being something which occurred in his past, admits that there has to be some other way in which ‘birth’ can be present, and if he admits that he doesn’t see that way, he might make the effort to find it out, and than eventually see it. [back]

Appearance and Existence

[source]

For a puthujjana the world exists. He can perceive things in that world, see them appear and disappear, he can see them changing. A puthujjana can also affect his surroundings and modify things according to own preferences, pursue the desirable experiences and avoid the undesirable ones—the puthujjana is involved. This ‘involvement’ with things represents the very core of the puthujjana’s ‘experience as a whole’. Most people spend the majority of their lives obliviously absorbed in it, taking the course of ‘involvement’ for granted.[1]

It needs to be understood that these ‘objects’, which the puthujjana is fundamentally involved with, are things which his experience is inseparable from, for the simple virtue of being his experience of those things. For this reason we have to broaden the meaning of the term ‘things’, from usually denominating ‘objects’ in one’s surroundings, to include any experience whatsoever that arises and can be discerned internally or externally (whether it is ‘objects’, ‘tools’, emotions’ or ‘thoughts’). In that way the term ‘things’ would correspond to what is meant by Pāli term ‘dhamma’. Thus, the experience of the puthujjana’s everyday world, his possessions, his desires and fears, anxieties and happiness are all things or phenomena. All these phenomena are completely unknown in their nature. This is why it is crucial for a puthujjana to recognize that a nature of a thing exists. This existence is not ‘in’ the world of the objects that are ready-to-hand, not ‘in’ his mind, not even between the two—but, a thing exists as an experience. Strictly speaking that’s all that can be truthfully said, without resorting to presupposed theories, inductive observations and explanations of the experience—the only thing that a puthujjana can know for certain is that ‘there is an experience’. In this way it can be seen that a thing is, its ‘being’ appears and things such as pleasure, pain, emotional states, ideas, abstractions etc. that people have in their everyday lives, are in this way all real, they all come to exist as something that is there, that has appeared. No matter how ordinary or extraordinary one’s experience is or might be, whether it is common or unusual, that experience exists as such. Even if one is going through the most obscure, ambiguous states of one’s mind, those very states are valid in their nature (as obscure, as ambiguous); whether they are intimate and subjective or the most impersonal objective facts—they are all phenomena, they constitute the experience as a whole (which is also a phenomenon).

“We do not know what ‘Being’ means. But even if we ask, ‘What is “Being”?’, we keep within an understanding of the ‘is’, though we are unable to fix conceptually what that ‘is’ signifies. We do not even know the horizon in terms of which that meaning is to be grasped and fixed. But this vague average understanding of Being is still a Fact.

However much this understanding of Being (an understanding which is already available to us) may fluctuate and grow dim, and border on mere acquaintance with a word, its very indefiniteness is itself a positive phenomenon which needs to be clarified.[2]

The same is to be said for the even more complex categories of the puthujjana’s world, such as ‘actions’, ‘choices’, notions of ‘good’ and ‘bad’ and similar. They are not exempt from the phenomenological nature of things. Good or bad, skilful or not, these things manifest in one’s experience, and as such: they are real.

A very common passage from the Suttas which describes that which is known as the ‘mundane’ Right View:

Atthi dinnaṃ, atthi yiṭṭhaṃ, atthi hutaṃ, atthi sukatadukkaṭānaṃ kammānaṃ phalaṃ vipāko, atthi ayaṃ loko, atthi paro loko, atthi mātā, atthi pitā, atthi sattā opapātikā, atthi loke samaṇabrāhmaṇā sammaggatā sammāpaṭipannā ye imañca lokaṃ parañca lokaṃ sayaṃ abhiññā sacchikatvā pavedentī’ti

“There is what is given and what is offered and what is sacrificed; there is fruit and result of good and bad actions; there is this world and the other world; there is mother and father; there are spontaneously reborn beings; there are in the world good and virtuous recluses and brahmins who have realised for themselves by direct knowledge and declare this world and the other world.”

– (MN 117 / iii, 72)

This easily overlooked passage offers a very acute description of an authentic attitude of a puthujjana—the attitude of recognition and acknowledgment of the existence of things as phenomena (“there is…”). Someone might argue that one does not necessarily see the spontaneously reborn beings for example, but the point is that one should recognize the mere fact that there could be spontaneously reborn beings—the possibility of spontaneously reborn beings exists as such. And if one recognizes the validity of the appearance and existence of that possibility, an expectation of the concrete proof that can be obtained only through senses (i.e. one needs to see those beings) ceases to be relevant, in the same way that a view that a thing exists only if it can be experienced through the senses ceases. This attitude thus discloses the priority of the phenomenal nature of things (of one’s experience), over any other view which does not assert that priority. And it is because of this very lack of the correct priority that these kinds of views are wrong views (as far as freedom from suffering is concerned). Thus, whatever one’s experience is, whichever shape it might take—big or small, important or not, clear or ambiguous—that experience is there in its own phenomenological form. This by no means implies that such experience is necessarily understood, it simply means that it is recognized for what it is, even if that is as “something-which-is-not-understood”. This kind of ‘acknowledgement’ is the authenticity that we also find the existential philosophers often referring to. Together with authenticity, there comes the sense of the fundamental responsibility for one’s own existence[3] which is a necessary prerequisite for a puthujjana’s ‘mundane’ Right View)[3] (which can then lead further onwards toward the ‘supramundane’ Right View—the view of the Path). The reason why this attitude is a necessary prerequisite is because only with this attitude will a puthujjana be able to understand that he does not understand, and by doing so enable himself for understanding.”[5] The problem is, however, that if a common man denies that which is right in front of him in his day-to-day living, he denies the basic principles of his own experience. In other words he is denying the most immediate appearance of things. This results in phenomena not being seen at all. As long as this attitude persists that man is going to be deprived of the possibility of understanding the nature of the experience and consequently the nature of his own suffering. That man is inauthentic.[6] As the experience shows us this is all too easily done. All that is required is to simply never question the face value of one’s views of the world and the experience and to never look further from one’s immediate absorption in things.

For inauthentic man, when he does think about the nature of his experience and the world around him, his views would generally pertain to a common notion of a hidden reality behind the everyday world (either material or mental, depending on the direction his mind takes). What is meant by this is that he simply assumes that there is something more real or fundamental in relation to what he is or can experience. Simply put, if he was to assume a ‘mental’ type of reality, as something which underlies the present experience, he would fall into (one of the forms of) idealism; alternatively, if the reality was to have a more ‘material’ basis, he would fall into some form of materialism (or realism).[7] Either way, the puthujjana oscillates between the two.[8]

For example, in present times, a spiritual/mystical view of the hidden ‘Reality’ (one’s ‘true Self’, or ‘universal consciousness’) would be a form of idealism, while the very common and prevalent scientific objectification of the experience would most certainly come under materialism. These two can serve as the two prominent poles of the Wrong View spectrum.[9] These views differ from the Right View because as they are focused on developing and providing explanations of the nature of one’s experience, while failing to see that fundamentally they are derived from it. No matter how plausible and accurate a theory or an explanation of the origins and nature of the experience is, the fact is that experience, as a phenomenon, will always have to come first. This means that the explanation cannot be applied retrospectively to describe its own origin which is simultaneously present. Nevertheless, by maintaining this contradiction (which is an assumption) the actual structural order of the experience is assumed different. And since that’s all a puthujjana has in front of him, that assumed nature of the experience exists as such. Because of this, the nature of a wrong view is to provide a man with reasons and causes, which achieves nothing except concealing and contradicting the notion of the immediate appearance of things and one’s own existential responsibility. When Reality is hidden behind the appearances, which are then no more than ‘illusory’, whatever a puthujjana does and whatever he feels ceases to be relevant, even if it’s the most immediate and personal suffering. If it isn’t irrelevant just yet, a person with this kind of view will certainly strive in order to make it so by blending it into the all-embracing view that the world is nothing more than illusion, and as such whatever comes to be experienced in that world is disregarded because it doesn’t belong to Reality. Consequently, by not pertaining to Reality, the things in one’s environment can be ignored, and one will feel justified in doing so. Thus, for a puthujjana of this kind, things encountered in everyday life don’t fit into his view of reality—they are dismissed, they are not understood.[10] In the view of scientific objectification on the other hand, the puthujjana’s actions are neatly explained in terms of various collections of nerve impulses, reflexes, genes, sensations and so on. In this case the significance of one’s actions cannot extend beyond the threshold of the molecular compounds of one’s body, which then serves as the reason (or excuse) for the puthujjana’s desires, emotions, concerns etc.[11] In both types of views the responsibility for the immediate intentions and decisions is abolished, by way of being included in the mystical or molecular forms (for example “God’s Will” or genetic “predispositions”)—which serve to explain one’s world. In either case that responsibility is not felt, its nature is disowned. (Might this perhaps be the real purpose of these views?) Thus, the inauthenticity remains for as long as there is a view which places itself over the existence as such, as something which is more primordial in itself: the Reality behind or beneath the appearance, the molecular structure of the world, again—beneath the things in the way we encounter them in the world. Consequently, things like ‘good’ or ‘bad’, ‘results’ (of one’s actions), ‘being reborn’, ‘sacrifice’, ‘other world’ and so on[12] have no place in one’s experience.[13] As such, they become very ambiguous categories of one’s life, which an individual can choose to accept and believe in, or perhaps reject according to his personal choice. (The overall decline of morality in the world indicates which kind of choice prevails.) In this way these things are pushed in the domain of religion and ethics and regarded as ‘convictions’ and ‘observances’ that one can follow if one pleases.

Thus, whenever the priority of existence is not recognized, the nature of things is obscured. Clearly the practice of Dhamma is then out of the question. Nevertheless, for a puthujjana the possibility of seeing the structural priority of existence as a whole over the particular instances his Self derives from it, still remains, and only when he admits this, the real work can begin.

The Appearance in Its Priority

So, with the mystical view on one end, and the objective, scientific one on the other, the recognition of one’s personal existence cannot arise. Because of these inauthentic attitudes, which are nevertheless normal attitudes of the puthujjana’s everyday life, it would be correct to say that for him things don’t even exist, in a correct sense of that word. Only with the development of the rudimentary notions of authenticity, through the practice of mindfulness and restraint and reflection, can a puthujjana begin to notice, little by little, the nature of his experience as a whole—phenomena can start to appear. It is only in this way that one can understand what is meant by the ‘being’ of things, which is nothing fundamentally different than the ‘being’ of myself.[14] Through the establishing of authenticity a puthujjana can observe that things around him, and his experience as a whole, appear and disappear. In the beginning it seems like this is happening while his sense of the experience as a whole stays unchanged. This ‘unchangedness’ holds priority over the puthujjana’s experience, and that’s because in its nature it presents itself as something which is remaining the same or independent (i.e. unchanging) throughout the appearance of things which comes and goes. It looks as if things that appear are ‘included’ within that general non-changing sense of the experience. The appearance of things —or, simply, things belong to it. Although there is no concealed ‘Being’ behind that which appears since the basic authenticity has been established, this nevertheless results in the notion that fundamentally things are, and that is why they appear. Thus, ‘Being’ is assumed to be an ontological phenomenon that manifests itself through the ‘appearance’. One might not be able to find it apart from appearance, but nevertheless, a puthujjana thinks—“things exist, that’s why they can appear”. In this way one assumes the ontological priority of existence over the appearance. Thus, a puthujjana places ‘being’ as that which is first. This type of priority of ‘being’, is the necessary basis for the puthujjana’s sense of ‘Self’. The notion of constancy, the unchanging nature of the experience as a whole, the independence, is the “extra-temporal changeless ‘self”’[15] of the puthujjana. ‘(The being of) Self’ is then the reason for things to appear ,they are appearing for it.[16] This arrangement, this particular [dis]order of things is also called: sakkāyadiṭṭhi.

If, presumably, a puthujjana wants to abandon this view, which is the root of all suffering, the authentic pursuit must continue. What he has to see is that this notion of ‘Self’, despite its independent character, also appears. No matter how elusive or ambiguous it might be—it has to be seen as such: as an elusive thing. Only after this is it is possible for a puthujjana to see that the order of things imposed by the presence of an assumed ‘extra-temporal’ phenomena in his experience is the wrong order. Based on things’ appearance, and based on the sense of the experience as a whole, there is no justifiable reason for him to assume any primacy of the sense of unchangeability any longer. There is ‘the sense of unchangeability’ and that too appears. Thus, the unchanging ‘(sense of) being’ was, in a wholly gratuitous manner, given priority over the appearance of things by being assumed as something which does not appear. The reason for this was simply because this notion of priority was never noticed.[17] If a puthujjana sees this existing notion that appears, (which is that, which is his ‘Self’), a sight of inseparability between ‘existence’ and ‘appearance’ will emerge. If a thing exists, that is because it appears; if it appears, that is it exists. Neither the appearance nor existence can be discerned or conceived without each other, and that is what is meant by “to be is to be perceived”—esse est percipi. At this phase, the assumption of a hidden reality behind the appearance is almost inconceivable. The puthujjana understands that if anything is to exist, it has to appear.[18]

Thus, one’s authenticity grows. The attitude has undergone a considerable change, from a puthujjana not even being aware of his own existence, over the notion that things appear because they exist, up to now, where ‘to appear’ and ‘to exist’ means just the same. Although this is certainly far better than anything before, nevertheless this attitude doesn’t quite yet free the puthujjana from suffering. He has to continue, but this is as far as he can go on his own. No matter how hard he tries to understand the existence, any attempt to do so will throw him onto the appearance, and vice versa—whenever he looks at the appearance all he is going to see is the existence. In one way or another, the puthujjana will not be able to prevent himself from falling into a view that ‘appearance’ and ‘existence’ are the same,[19] or—since the difference is perceived between them—he might think that they are different.[20] But then the ‘sameness’ is still there, so perhaps they are both-the-same-and-different. Consequently, he can negate the whole thing and think that they are neither-the-same-nor-different. In either case, he remains ignorant in regard to the two; he remains a puthujjana. If he is to change this, he needs help from the outside; it has to come to him externally. The puthujjana is not able (i.e. it is structurally impossible) to “step out” of his experience, and see his situation of ‘being-a-puthujjana’ as a whole. No matter how far he steps back, he carries his ignorance with him. Only coming across the Buddha’s Teaching can offer him an outside perspective of himself, which if cultivated can ‘turn him’ into a non-puthujjana.[21]

The Teaching tells him that ‘existence’ cannot be conceived anywhere apart from ‘appearance’, but also that it is not ‘appearance’ as such; furthermore, and even more importantly, it also tells him that ‘existence’ does not depend on ‘appearance’ directly, it depends on the ‘assumption’ (upādāna)[22] in regard to that which appears,[23] and this means nothing else then that the appearance, for its appearing, does not require existence at all—it is actually better without it.[24]

Na kho, āvuso visākha, taññeva upādānaṃ te pañcupādānakkhandhā, nāpi aññatra pañcahupādānakkhandhehi upādānaṃ. Yo kho, āvuso visākha, pañcasu upādānakkhandhesu chandarāgo taṃ tattha upādānan”ti

“The five assumed aggregates, friend Visākha, are not just assuming; but neither is there assumption apart from the five assumed aggregates. That, friend Visākha, in the five assumed aggregates which is desire-&-lust, that assumption is therein.”

– (MN 44 / i, 299-300)

Thus this inquiry has passed ‘through’ the puthujjana’s ‘being’, which must not be either denied (dismissed) or justified (explained), but established as a phenomenon. It was seen that this phenomenon, far from being a reason because of which things appear, actually depends on the puthujjana’s assumption in regard to that which appears. In the beginning, the puthujjana’s existence was a mere fact, of which he was barely aware and this fact represented his thoroughly inauthentic Self. However, now his existence has not only ‘appeared’ for him, it was seen that ‘existence’ cannot even be conceived without that which appears. In this way the roles were slowly reversed and the priority of existence over the appearance of things has faded. Now, with the Buddha’s aid, a puthujjana can further see that actually the existence is not that which appears—it never was. It is the appearance that exists, by him assuming it (or by being ignorant in regard to it.) The existence, in order to be, requires maintaining (hence upādānapaccāya bhavo). In this way a new perspective has emerged on the relationship between existence and appearance, which reveals that, initially, the puthujjana had the whole picture upside-down. The further pursuit of this principle would simply carry further right through the center of puthujjana’s being (who at that point would cease to be a puthujjana) and complete the ‘reversal’ of this inverted experience of his, in the same manner as one would turn a sleeve inside-out. At that point that individual’s Being would cease without remainder.

“Husserl attempts to make the natural attitude descriptively evident by pointing out that our everyday way of going about our business—dealing with things of all sorts, other people, engaged in scientific activities, recreation, and so on – involves various modalities of “belief.” I simply take for granted that what I am dealing with exists and is, more or less, as it presents itself as being. Furthermore, “other actual objects are there for me as determinate, as more or less well known, without being themselves perceived or, indeed, present in any other mode of intuition” (Husserl 1982: 51)—that is, they belong within a co-intended horizon of “indeterminate actuality” (Husserl 1982:52).”—‘The Blackwell Companion to Phenomenology and Existentialism’, Husserlian Phenomenology (by Simon Crowell), p. 19. [back]

Martin Heidegger, Being and Time, translated by J. Macquarrie and E.S. Robinson. London: SCM Press, 1962, p. 25. [back]

A rather inspired observation of Walter Kaufmann, a distinguished Nietzsche scholar and translator, in his book Existentialism from Dostoevsky to Sartre, p. 46: “…perhaps the most compassionate and venerable of all mortals, the Buddha. . . [had said that] all man’s alibis are unacceptable: no gods are responsible for his condition; no original sin; no heredity and no environment; no race, no caste, no father, and no mother; no wrong-headed education, no governess, no teacher; not even an impulse or a disposition, a complex or a childhood trauma. Man is free; but his freedom does not look like the glorious liberty of the Enlightenment; it is no longer the gift of God. Once again, man stands alone in the universe, responsible for his condition, likely to remain in a lowly state, but free to reach above the stars.” [back]

“There is fruit and result of good and bad action…”, i.e.: “I am responsible for what I do”. Similarly, “there are… recluses and brahmins who have realised for themselves the direct knowledge…” means “Freedom from suffering is possible, and if I don’t pursue it, I, myself, am responsible for that. By not pursuing it I am responsible for remaining there where suffering can arise—I am responsible for my suffering.” [back]

“It is far better for a man to understand that he does not understand the Dhamma, than it is for him to believe falsely that he does understand it. The former attitude may encourage progress, the latter can only obstruct it.”—CtP, pp. 57-58. [back]

For more on the everyday phenomenon of ‘inauthenticity’ see Hedigger, Being and Time, and J-P. Sartre, Being and Nothingess, particularly the chapter on ‘Bad Faith’. See also the following lines from Kierkegaard’s Concluding Unscientific Postscript (p. 311): “Science organizes the moments of subjectivity within a knowledge of them, and this knowledge is assumed to be the highest stage, and all knowledge is an abstraction which annuls existence, a taking of the objects of knowledge out of existence. In existence, however, such a principle does not hold. If thought speaks deprecatingly of the imagination, imagination in its turn speaks deprecatingly of thought; and likewise with the feeling. The task is not to exalt the one at the expense of the other, but to give them an equal status, to unify them in simultaneity; the medium in which they are unified is existence.” [back]

Ven. Ñāṇavīra observes: “There is, however, another point: an oriented world (which is the meaning of loka in the Suttas) is the correlative of a point of view (there is a SN Sutta that specifically identifies the world with the eye, ear, nose, and so on), and consequently to deny self is to deny the world, and to assert self is to assert the world (so loko so attā). Thus we have the following scheme: Sassatavāda Assert a point of view; Asserts self— atthi attāti; Assert the world; Denies the objective existence of things— sabbaṃ natthīti Is an Idealist (Bradley, Berkeley) Uccedavāda Denies a point of view; Denies self— natthi attāti; Denies the world; Asserts the objective existence of things— sabbaṃ atthīti Is a Realist (Stebbing, Russell) If this analysis is correct it would explain why a scientist, though apparently asserting the permanence of the Universe, is, in fact, an ucchedavādin—the Universe he asserts is without a point of view, and is the negation of the world (= loka).”—StP, p. 186. Also, cf. DN 2, in particular the Ajita Kesakambalin’s response. [back]

Cf. StP, p. 323. [back]

Obviously things can be a bit more complex than this, inasmuch as these opposite views have a lot in common as Merleau-Ponty observes: “We pass from absolute objectivity to absolute subjectivity, but this second idea is not better than the first and is upheld only against it, which means by it. The affinity between intellectualism and empiricism is thus much less obvious and much more deeply rooted than is commonly thought. It arises not only from the anthropological definition of sensation used equally by both, but from the fact that both persist in the natural or dogmatic attitude, and the survival of sensation in intellectualism is merely a sign of this dogmatism. Intellectualism accepts as completely valid the idea of truth and the idea of being in which the formative work of consciousness culminates and is embodied, and its alleged reflection consists in positing as powers of the subject all that is required to arrive at these ideas. The natural attitude, by throwing me into the world of things, gives me the assurance of apprehending a ‘real’ beyond appearance, the ‘true’ beyond illusion.”—Merleau-Ponty, Phenomenology of Perception, p. 45. [back]

“To have faith in the Reality of the ‘external world’, whether rightly or wrongly; to “prove” this Reality for it, whether adequately or inadequately; to presuppose it, whether explicitly or not—attempts such as these which have not mastered their own basis with full transparency, presuppose a subject which is proximally worldless or unsure of its world, and which must, at bottom, first assure itself of a world. Thus, from the very beginning, Being-in-a-world is disposed to “take things” in some way [Auffassen], to suppose, to be certain, to have faith—a way of behaving which itself is always a founded mode of Being-in-the-world. The ‘problem of Reality’ in the sense of the question whether an external world is present-at-hand and whether such world can be proved, turns out to be an impossible one, not because its consequences lead to inextricable impasses, but because the very entity which serves as its theme, is one which, as it were, repudiates any such formulation of the question. Our task is not to prove that an ‘external world’ is present-at-hand or to show how it is present-at-hand, but to point out why Dasein, as Being-in-the-world, has the tendency to bury the ‘external world’ in nullity ‘epistemologically’ before going on to prove it. The reason for this lies in Dasein’s falling and in the way in which the primary understanding of Being has been diverted to Being as presence-at-hand—a diversion which is motivated by that falling itself.”—Heidegger, op. cit. p. 250. [back]

“Behaviour is thus hidden by the reflex, the elaboration and patterning of stimuli, by a longitudinal theory of nervous functioning, which establishes a theoretical correspondence between each element of the situation and an element of the reaction… “The traditional notion of sensation was not a concept born of reflection, but a late product of thought directed towards objects, the last element in the representation of the world, the furthest removed from its original source, and therefore the most unclear. Inevitably science, in its general effort towards objectification, evolved a picture of the human organism as a physical system undergoing stimuli which were themselves identified by their physico-chemical properties, and tried to reconstitute actual perception on this basis, and to close the circle of scientific knowledge by discovering the laws governing the production of knowledge itself, by establishing an objective science of subjectivity…”—Merleau-Ponty, op. cit. pp. 8, & 12. [back]

Things that are not explainable through the observational methods of inductive sciences. [back]

“The theory of sensation, which builds up all knowledge out of determinate qualities, offers us objects purged of all ambiguity, pure and absolute, the ideal rather than the real themes of knowledge.”—Merleau-Ponty, op. cit. p. 13. [back]

A reader might notice here the discrepancy between what I’ve just said and the views one can find in Heidegger’s or Sartre’s works. These philosophers maintain the notion (in different degrees) of the separation between my being, i. e. the ‘I’, and being of things, the objects of the experience which ‘I’ encounters. For example Sartre developed a fundamental division of being-in-itself and being-for-itself, which he then tried, and consequently failed, to reconcile in Being and Nothingess. In-itself is not more real than for-itself, (i. e. ‘me’ or ‘[my] consciousness’), and the reverse is also true; in order for it to exist it requires for-itself, as much as for-itself requires the in-itself. And it is not possible, in good faith, to think of or regard the in-itself independently of consciousness, nor consciousness independently of the in-itself, not even in one’s imagination. ‘Matter’, rūpa, needs consciousness in order to find its footing in appearance, without it, it is inconceivable. (Cf. the mutually dependent relationship between nāmarūpa and viññāṇa.) In brief: whenever there are things, there is me; whenever there is me, there are things. (Hence one has to understand sabbe dhamma anatta—all things are not-self.) Whether it is ‘being’ of things that we are looking at, or my ‘being’, the point is that there is ‘being’—bhava is there. This is also why, the reader will notice I use ‘existence’ and ‘being’ interchangeably. Whether it is ‘mine’, or not, whether it is personal or impersonal, large or small, visible or invisible, far or near, any ‘being’ whatsoever means that bhava is there; it is, it exists. As long as that is the case, ‘I’ (or at least some degree of the conceit ‘I am’) will be present. [back]

NoD, ATTĀ. [back]

“…the phenomenon remains, for “to appear” supposes in essence somebody to whom to appear. “—J.—P. Sartre, Being and Nothingness, translated by Hazel E. Barnes. London: Methuen, 1957, 1969; New York: Philosophical Library, 1957, p. 2. [back]

Hence the nature of it also appearing was obscured. [back]

Sartre (op. cit. , p. 6) seems to have become aware of this, but then chose to disagree: “What determines the being of the appearance is the fact that it appears. And since we have restricted reality to the phenomenon, we can say of the phenomenon that it is as it appears. Why not push the idea to its limit and say that the being of the appearance is its appearing? This is simply a way of choosing new words to clothe the old “Esse est percipi”of Berkeley… It seems that the famous formula of Berkeley cannot satisfy us—for two essential reasons, one concerning the nature of percipi, the other that of the percipere.” Sartre then goes on to construe consciousness into a form of an ‘empty’ absolute which is “pure ‘appearance’ in the sense that it exists only to the degree to which appears. “ (op. cit., p. 12). There is no question of things existing to the degree they appear, however there is no such thing as ‘pure appearance’ in the sense of appearance independent of that which has appeared, since every appearance has to be appearance of something. Even if someone says: “Pure appearance”—that designation of that “pure appearance” is that which stands for that which is “pure appearance”, thus that “pure appearance” is not pure—Sartre’s “empty absolute” is thus contradictio in terminis. [back]

“The first being which we meet in our ontological inquiry is the being of the appearance. Is it itself an appearance?… In other words, is the being which discloses itself to me, which appears to me, of the same nature as the being of existents which appear to me?”—Sartre, op. cit. p. 4. [back]

“…the being of the phenomenon can not be reduced to the phenomenon of being.”—Sartre, op. cit. p. 6. [back]

“The puthujjana’s experience is (saṅkhāra-)dukkha from top to bottom, and the consequence is that he has no way of knowing dukkha for himself; for however much he ‘steps back’ from himself in a reflexive effort he still takes dukkha with him…””—CtP, p. 482; and on the p. 38 of the same work: “The Dhamma gives the puthujjana the outside view of avijjā, which is inherently unobtainable for him by unaided reflexion (in the ariyasāvaka this view has, as it were, ‘taken’ like a graft, and is perpetually available.” [back]

Upādāna is defined by the PTS Pali-English Dictionary as follows: 1) lit. substratum by means of which an active process is kept alive or going; fuel, supply, provision… 2) ‘drawing upon’, grasping, taking up…; Assumption, assuming according to Chambers Concise Dictionary means: to adopt, to take in, to take upon oneself, to take for granted; [Latin term is assūměre, assumptum: (ad) to (sūměre) take]. The nature of the assumption in general, can be described as follows: the assumption takes its object for granted, and it does so without having a knowledge of whether that thing which is being ‘taken up’ actually is in the way that it is taken up. As a matter of fact, not having a knowledge of this is the fundamental prerequisite for the assumption to manifest, because if the object is known for what it is, there wouldn’t be a need to assume it for what it is. Knowledge and assumption (vijjā and upādāna) are mutually exclusive. However, upādāna is there (as pañc’upādānakkhandā) which means that the assumption of what the five aggregates are, preceeds that which five aggregates are. In this way the beginingless avijjā puts the assumption first, as something “in front”, something more fundamental, that the five aggregates which are taken up. This is done in direct violation of the fact that upādāna cannot be anywhere apart from the five aggregates, that it actually requires them for its existence. Thus, assumption assumes priority over that which is already there. That ‘assumed assumption’ (or taking for granted that which is taken for granted) becomes the puthujjana’s ‘norm’ of things’ existence, it ‘measures’ them according what it thinks they are, not for what they are. The extent of the assumption determines the extent of this measure (i. e. the existence)— upādānapaccāya bhavo. (Cf. Sartre, op. cit., p. 2: “…then the appearance becomes full positivity; its essence is an ‘appearing’ which is no longer opposed to being but on the contrary is the measure of it.”) [back]

He assumes: “It is the same; it is different; it is both-the-same-and-different; it is neither-the-same-nor-different.” [back]

“Craving, however, is a gratuitous (though beginningless) parasite on the intentional structure described here, and its necessity is not to be deduced from the necessity of intention in all experience. Intention does not imply craving—a hard thing to understand!”—NoD, CETANĀ. [back]

Hierarchy of Awareness

[source]

The fundamental nature of our experience can be described as a hierarchy, which Ven. Ñāṇavīra tried to explain in his FUNDAMENTAL STRUCTURE (NoD). We are what we experience, it is not possible to view (or imagine) this hierarchy from ‘outside’, independent of us, because regardless of how far one steps back, one cannot abandon the experience as such.

The experience, whether mundane or sublime, possesses certain characteristics, and the most prominent among them is that it is hierarchically ordered. This hierarchy goes into infinity in both directions, and this is something which can be seen from the nature of particulars and generals. If we take a look at our own experience as it is, we can see that there are two aspects which appear as being more pronounced than anything else. Those aspects are known as immediacy and reflexion. Together they comprise this hierarchy of the experience as a whole. Thus, the hierarchy we have been referring to can be called reflexive hierarchy.[1] If we want to be more precise we can say that immediacy and reflexion, respectively, represent two different modes of experiencing this hierarchy. In immediacy, reflexion is not directly present; it is there, but placed in the background. In reflexion, the immediate object is seen from an additional point of view, which means that once we reflect upon something, immediacy does not disappear, it rather becomes secondary to the field of attention but, nevertheless, it remains there:

“In immediate experience the thing is present; in reflexive experience the thing is again present, but as implicit in a more general thing. Thus in reflexion the thing is twice present, once immediately and once reflexively. This is true of reflexion both in the loose sense (as reflection or discursive thinking) and a fortiori in the stricter sense (for the reason that reflection involves reflexion, though not vice versa). See MANO and also VIÑÑĀṆA.” (NoD, ATTĀ (a))

The presence of this reflexive hierarchy, as can be seen from FUNDAMENTAL STRUCTURE,[2] generates another dimension to the experience. This dimension is also hierarchically ordered, superimposed upon the original reflexive one; dependent upon it, but at the same time responsible for the existence of it. This simply means that their type of dependence is not temporal, i.e. it does not occur in sequence. This new hierarchy is the hierarchy of awareness, and although this hierarchy cannot go ‘below’ the experience as such (awareness is always awareness of something in-the-world), there is no limit for ascending levels of this hierarchy. As the term ‘generating’ implies, with the presence of reflexive hierarchy the hierarchy of awareness is also present—simultaneously; and as was already said, the existence of this hierarchy, makes the reflexion possible in the first place.

Let us try and say something more about the nature of superimposition, which is relevant for these two hierarchies. When things are superimposed they are not directly or linearly related. They are simply there, next to each other and any thought along the lines of causality distorts them as they are.[3] This superimposed way of existing is nothing else than what is meant by being akālika, ‘timeless’ or ‘beyond time’. Two things are there, dependent, yet not directly related to each other. That is the reason why we said that with the presence of reflexive hierarchy there is the presence of the hierarchy of awareness. This precedes any notions of causality or of time. Nevertheless, if we still insist on describing their mutual relationship, the most accurate way would be to simply say: with reflexion, awareness is; without reflexion awareness is not. This is clearly a reference to paṭiccasamuppāda itself, so now would be the right time to say something more about it.

Paṭiccasamuppāda is a principle of timeless dependence, i.e. existential superimposition. With the presence of one thing the other thing is simultaneously present, too. Thus, it is not possible to conceive or imagine paṭiccasamuppāda without actually seeing it within the experience, simply because conceiving and imagining, in its nature, involves sequence (i.e. it is linear from the point of view of this new hierarchy, and as such pertains solely to the reflexive hierarchy). So, although hierarchy of awareness cannot go ‘under’ or ‘in front’ of the immediate-and-reflexive experience, as we noted above, it can always come ‘closer’ than it is.[4] The point is that these two hierarchies do not touch or overlap, they are perpendicular.[5] When we say ‘hierarchy of awareness’, this should not be understood in a sense that one is always aware. On the contrary, revealing this hierarchy requires effort, which is being manifested through the practice of mindfulness. Nevertheless, this hierarchy exists, and because of that the whole other reflexive hierarchy is possible (see above). The difficulty lies in the fact that this hierarchy cannot be directly grasped, and that is because any notions of directionality originate from it.

The description made so far refers to the experience as a whole in an ideal sense, i.e. the structure of experience has been described and this structure is the same in arahant and puthujjana. The difficulty is that the experience is, when we reflect upon it, already affected with ignorance (avijjā). Ultimately, ignorance is nothing but the non-seeing of the nature of superimposition of the two hierarchies. Things are further complicated by the fact that even reflexive hierarchy is not a simple order of different levels of generality of things; even in this hierarchy, those levels are, in a way, superimposed in relation to each other, and they are all ‘kept together’, so to speak, by the fact that they can all be attended to from the perspective of the hierarchy of awareness. This hierarchy unifies them, determines them or ‘keeps them together’. Here we can recognize the nature of determination (saṅkhāra), which, as the Suttas tell us, exist through the presence of ignorance (avijjāpaccayā saṅkhāra). Thus, when one is not free from igorance, the nature of the hierarchy of awareness is not understood and because of that, that hierarchy will be implicitly taken par value, as a kind of owner-creator of the reflexive one, i.e. of our experience. This hierarchy of awareness appears as being towards the reflexive hierarchy, as if ‘pressing’ in the direction of it.[6] Simply by not-seeing that it is directly dependent upon the reflexive hierarchy, this ‘pressing’ of the hierarchy of awareness is being followed at its face value, and one comes to assume and accept that offered ownership over one’s own experience,[7], i.e. one comes to assume that there actually is Self.

This is perhaps overly-simplified. As we said earlier on, the reflexive hierarchy generates the presence of the hierarchy of awareness. This in return, simultaneously determines reflexive hierarchy as such. However, since there is no first moment of ignorance being manifested, both of those hierarchies are affected by it, through and through. The hierarchy of awareness appears as somehow ‘in between’ our reflexive levels of experience, and that is what Ven. Ñāṇavīra meant by saying that they are perpendicular (see footnote 2). As a result of the presence of ignorance, this ‘owner’ which we mentioned above also appears like something which is somewhere within our experience, ‘neither here nor there’. This elusiveness is maintained by the lack of one’s capability of an indirect approach,[8] and as a result this ‘owner’ becomes identified with reflexive or immediate or reflexive-and-immediate or non-reflexive-nor-immediate aspects of life. In structural terms, simply not seeing this ‘towards’ of the hierarchy of awareness, makes the experience distorted, and following it means that one is going ‘with the grain’—anuloma. Only, when ‘towards’ is indirectly seen as being directly dependent upon things which are impermanent, then the hierarchy of awareness will lose its ‘pressure’ and remain standing there, “cut off at the root, like a palm stump.” (MN 72 / i, 487) At this point the actual hierarchy is paṭiloma, ‘against the grain’, i.e. ‘towards’ is seen as impermanent and because of that it ceases to be the reason of one’s actions, i.e. Self is destroyed.

Thus, Self is the reason for the existence of Self, i.e. both reflexion and immediacy are equally affected by it. Only when reflexion-and-immediacy are seen as a whole as being determined by something else, the nature of the Self becomes revealed, which is that it is not-Self (neither owner nor master). Thus, that thing which was regarded as Self, does not disappear upon realization of anicca and dukkha, it ‘changes direction’, so to speak, and becomes not-Self, anattā. However, even then, the thing remains there and what disappears is Self-view,[9] and that is because the hierarchy of awareness has lost its ‘pressure’;[10] thus certain assumptions in regard to reflexive hierarchy disappear.

For more on this subject see CtP, L. 93, pp. 351f. It is not possible to clarify the point any further, simply because of the nature of the subject. When one reflects, in a strict sense (i.e. reflexion), one is aware. What is then present in one’s experience is hierarchy of awareness together with those things that were reflected upon, i.e. revealed by reflexion. [back]

NoD, FUNDAMENTAL STRUCTURE , Static Aspect, §16. [back]

Yena yena hi maññanti, tato taṃ hoti aññathā, “In whatever terms they conceive it, it turns into something other than that.” (Sn 3.12) [back]

This is achieved in the practice of jhāna, which, however, will not concern us here.[back]

NoD, FUNDAMENTAL STRUCTURE , Static Aspect, §16. [back]

“It is in the nature of the pañc’upādānakkhandhā to press for recognition, in one way or another, as ‘self’.” (NoD, PARAMATTHA SACCA , §6) [back]

One does not see that the ‘owner’ depends upon his ownership. [back]

By an ‘indirect approach’ we imply seeing the nature of superimposition. As it was outlined above, the direct approach has been taken in this essay as linear, and as such it is incapable of reaching and understanding the hierarchy of awareness in a proper way (see the fifth paragraph). The indirect approach refers to seeing that with the presence of what, does this arise, and with the absence of what, does this cease. In other words, this is a phenomenological approach, or an approach founded upon sati, whereby the immediate things of experience are not directly followed at its initial appearance. [back]

View originating from the Self. [back]

Only an arahat is completely free from this pressing nature of experience. The case with other sekhā is that ‘pressure’ varies in degrees. [back]

Papañca-Saññā-Sankhā

[source]

This compound has represented, to paraphrase John D. Ireland from his Udāna translation notes, a stumbling block which even the ancient commentaries find difficult to define. If the importance of the term is to be deduced from the extent of its difficulty then indeed understanding of this compound carries a lot of significance in regard to grasping of the Buddha’s Teaching.

There are various translations of papañca-saññā-sankhā, with currently the most prominent ones being either Ven. Bhikkhu Bodhi’s “notions [born of] mental proliferations” translating the term papañca as ‘proliferation’; or Ven. Ñāṇamoli Thera’s “calculations of perceptions of diversifications” where he renders papañca as ‘diversification’. Beyond these two, plus the PTS Dictionary definition, I am not familiar in detail with any other different interpretations of this compound. I am aware that Ven. Ñāṇananda in his “Concept and Reality in Early Buddhist Thought” addresses this topic to a certain degree and also that Ven. Bhikkhu Bodhi based his views of the term upon this interpretation[1] but I, myself, have never actually read Ven. Ñāṇananda’s book so my view on this matter will come from perhaps, to some extent, a different angle.

To start with, the respective terms ‘diversification’ and ‘proliferation’ do not deviate from the meaning of papañca. According to the PTS dictionary, papañca is “expansion, diffuseness, manifoldedness” or “obstacle, hindrance or delay”. The other members of the compound are defined as saññā (perception) and sankhā (sign or characteristic). So the above-mentioned translations would, to some degree, convey the nature of papañca-saññā-sankhā quite accurately and, as Ven. Bhikkhu Bodhi says in The Middle Length Discourses of the Buddha[2] (endnote no. 229, p. 1204-5), “no rendering [of this compound] is utterly beyond doubt”. The question which raises itself then is not how to etymologically trace the exact roots and origination of the compound, since such, a task in this case proves impossible in the absolute sense (and many seem to agree with this). Rather, it is better to focus and try to find out within one’s own experience and practice what is implied existentially and phenomenologically in the Suttas by this term.

At the risk of being incomprehensible on some points, I would try to use ‘descriptive’ language, rather than overly technical terms as people’s general views are already quite firm in regard to such terminology and it is very likely that they will be coming from a quite different place than me, probably too different which could obstruct them from understanding what I’m trying to say. In order to reduce this possibility to a minimum I thought of using some more common terms in my descriptions which carry less chance of being misunderstood. I hope I won’t miss the mark too much.

Those familiar with phenomenology and the philosophy of existence should not have any problems in understanding a statement like all our experience is intentional or teleological or simply—significant. Each thing (dhamma) which is being experienced in our everyday life has, as its inherent nature, to point to other thing(s), within the experience as a whole. The thing’s significance is not something ‘steady’ or ‘inchangeable’, although it often might appear so. The significance of a thing is, rather, something which is being acquired through the repetition of the respective experiences of that very thing. During this, the whole perception of a thing comes to ‘grow’ in a course of time, so to speak, and though there are certainly significances which are recognized as common to all people, at a more fundamental level they are all individually acquired and carried by each of us[3].

Without going into greater details let us say that in the Suttas this intentionality of experience is what is meant by the statement “with the grain” or anuloma. Actually, it is probably better to be more precise and to re-qualify this and say: taking for granted this intentionality, holding it and appropriating it, makes this with of “with the grain” to appear. In the arahant’s case, the ignorance is completely destroyed, yet the grain still remains, i.e. things do not stop pointing to other things, but this ‘with’ ceases to exist and is being replaced by ‘against’ as a result of which we get “against the grain”—patiloma. What has changed is the fundamental direction of regarding this very directionality of experience. Thus, even in the case of complete liberation things continue to be teleological or ‘with purpose’ so they still point to other things and so on. All this is being mentioned for the reason that the term papañca is probably too often misunderstood to simply mean ‘mental proliferation’, ‘when one thinks or analyzes too much’ or something like that. Although these things do imply papañca (or to be more precise ignorance and desire-and-lust), the above said nevertheless shows us that if papañca is anything, it is certainly more fundamental than that. In support of this we may add that papañca is frequently linked with maññanā, ‘conceving’ (for which see Mūlapariyāya Sutta, MN 1) which certainly represents the most fundamental ‘occurrence’ in a mind affected with ignorance. Thus, what papañca would imply is nothing less than this very intentionality of our experience and its tendency to grow and expand. However this can happen only when that ‘with’ is present i.e. when the mind is not free from the bonds of ignorance and when it keeps following things in their appearance— “…his consciousness flows after the sign of form [sound, smell, tastes, touches, thoughts], is tied and shackled by gratification in the sign of form, if fettered by the fetter of gratification…”[4]. And surely enough it is said that the arahant is nippapañca—without diversifications, free from any attachments (upadhi), free from burden accumulated in the past.

Thus, one’s world (everything which appears—nāma-rūpa), expands. One’s views, desires etc. expand too, yet this should not be understood in a momentary sense, which would suggest that they will somehow ‘shrink’ afterwards[5] by themselves. Their intensity or the intensity of their presence, once ‘accumulated’ i.e. came to being, is being ‘assumed’ or ‘held’ (upādāna) at that (new) face value. When this happens—and it happens through the repetition of [ignorant] actions as said above—consciousness “becomes established” upon that degree of presence, which then becomes the actual experience of that thing. Thus, the intensity of experience, that which appears as nāma-rūpa grows (for more details see Mahānidāna Sutta, DN 15 [ii,63]). This kind of pattern stretches from the most fundamental levels of our existence (as seen in Mūlapariyāya Sutta), up to the coarsest ones which we might say are, “resorting to rods and weapons, of quarrels, brawls, disputes, recrimination, malicious words and false speech[6]…”, that is the directly painful actions resulting from one’s ignorance. Thus, based on the above, papañca represents the ‘diffusion’ of this fundamental underlying principle with ignorance being necessarily present, and consequently papañca-saññā-sankhā are all ‘calculations’ or ‘notions’, perceived and originated as a result of taking this principle of diffusion for granted i.e. not understanding it.

To conclude, it is worth mentioning that this whole situation would be much clearer if we can bear in mind Ven. Ñāṇavīra Thera’s description of the infinite hierarchy of consciousness, the different levels of generality of nāma-rūpa—viññāṇa. That is because papañca-saññā-sankhā is not something which appears on a voluntary level, as if one could stop it at any time; it stretches from the most general (reflexive) levels of existence[7]. What one is responsible for, in that whole structure, is “delighting in, welcoming and holding to…” the “source through which perceptions and notions [born of] mental proliferation beset a man…”[8]. Thus the hierarchy of signifying things continues to arise (cease and change-while-standing) but it no longer grows; it is “cut off at the root, made like a palm stump”. Its root was ignorance in itself and with its absence everything founded upon it comes to an end—one is free. In other words the respective experiences of the puthujjana and arahant alike, share the same fundamental nature of impermanence (arising and ceasing) but the respective intensities of those experiences are changed; for the arahant feeling none of it)[9] and for the puthujjana dependant on the amount of ignorance being present. More ignorance, more ‘intensity’, things appear as more ‘pressing’ and one is easily prone to giving in to desire-and-lust. The arising of things in the puthujjana’s mind brings diffusion of perceptions and notions which, while not understood at its roots, will in return diffuse further and further and so on. This cannot happen in the arahant’s mind any more. His consciousness has ‘ceased’ so there is nothing to follow and diversify upon this teleological characteristic of the existential structure, which will remain only until his aggregates ‘break apart’.

: Which, as I will attempt to show in this essay, is over-simplified. [back]

Translated by Bhikkhu Ñāṇamoli and Bhikkhu Bodhi, Wisdom Publications, Third edition 2005. [back]

Preferences and values being perhaps too coarse yet a good enough example of this. [back]

: Uddhesavibhanga Sutta, MN 138. [iii,225] [back]

They would only do so in the arahant’s case. [back]

Madhupiṇḍika Sutta, MN 18; translation taken from The Middle Length Discourses of the Buddha, Bhikkhu Ñāṇamoli and Bhikkhu Bodhi, Wisdom Publications, Third edition 2005, p. 202 [i,109]. [back]

Compare also the nature of the five hindrances. It takes the first jhāna for one to be able to suppress them, which speaks for itself, since such strength of one’s concentration is enough for becoming an arahant (if there is wisdom, of course). [back]

op. cit. p. 202. [back]

Compare Ven. Sāriputta’s answer to Ven. Udāyi when the later asked him what is there that is pleasant when there is nothing felt [in nibbāna]—“Just this is pleasant, friend, that herein there is nothing felt”, AN iv,414. [back]

The Infinity of The Mind (Notes on AN 1.51)

[source]

Pabhassaramidaṃ, bhikkhave, cittaṃ. Tañca kho āgantukehi upakkilesehi upakkiliṭṭham. Taṃ assutavā puthujjano yathābhūtaṃ nappajānāti. Tasmā ‘assutavato puthujjanassa cittabhāvanā natthī’ti vadāmī”ti.

“Bright, monks, is the mind. It is superimposed by the defiling obstructions. The uninstructed worldling does not know this. For the uninstructed worldling, therefore, there is no development of mind.”

Pabhassaram—this could be translated as ‘bright’, and it should be regarded as something lit up, shining, effulgent or lucid. To find out how this term should be understood, one can bring to mind the term ākāsa—space—which literally means ‘shining forth’, in the sense of a space which is lit up. In MN 49, we can see that consciousness is referred to as viññāṇaṃ anidassanaṃ anantaṃ sabbato pabhaṃ, where ‘non-indicative’, ‘infinite’ (or endless, limitless) and ‘completely radiant’ (i.e. utterly and fundamentally lucid, not to be understood in a sense of mystically beaming rays of light or similar), are the terms referring to viññāṇa.[1] The whole point is that ‘brightness’ is an epithet describing the inherently infinite structure of the mind, which is ‘defiled’ by the obstructions (i.e. made finite). In SN 35.202 the Buddha said:

How, friends, does one not leak? Here, friends, having seen form with eye, a monk does not incline towards pleasing forms, he is not affected by displeasing forms. He lives aware of the body there and with mind that is boundless.

A monk can dwell and live his life with a “boundless mind”.[2] [3] He has understood the nature of the body there together with the arisen structure of the present experience,[4] which is infinite. By understanding the infinite or boundless, any boundaries and finiteness that were present as a result of that lack of understanding, are removed. In other words, the ‘brightness’ or ‘lucidity’ or ‘infinity’ or ‘boundlessness’ are the ways of describing the property of the fundamental structure of experience, which is the very reason why overcoming the obstructions is possible.

Āgantuka—here it is translated as ‘superimposed’. It can also mean adventitious, incidental, accessory. The main point that has to be borne in mind is that the ‘obstructions’ are “incidental”, in the sense that they are not caused by the pabhassaramidaṃ cittaṃ, but are nevertheless there. The defiling obstructions do not have anything in common with the brightness of the mind; they are simply “layered” there, superimposed without actually affecting the infinite structure. Thus, since the infinite mind does not need those obstructions, it can be rightly said that they are completely gratuitous.[5]

So, obstructions, or more precisely avijjā, have no first point when they are manifested before which mind was pure, bright and unpolluted. Because of this it is not correct to refer to ‘bright mind’ as an original thing, as if it existed in a pure state before the obstructions arrived. Since there is no beginning to the infinity, nor to the beginningless avijjā, the notions of “first this, then that” have no place to apply. So how shall this evident priority of the ‘bright mind’ be understood then? The answer is straight—in an atemporal, structural sense. The infinity of the mind precedes avijjā ontologically, so to speak, while they are there both, simultaneously present. This should also shed some light onto why the structure of the mind does not imply nor require the obstructions (hence they are called ‘obstructions’)—they are superfluous, unnecessary, superimposed. Yet, the uppakilesā are there, and are not to be found elsewhere.[6] To put this all in different words: the infinity of one’s mind is a temporally more fundamental than one’s own nescience in regard to it. Furthermore, it is because of the nescience in regard to the nature of infinity, that avijjā is a beginningless phenomenon. If infinity has no beginning, how could the fundamental ignorance of that be different?

This is not all, there are further implications of one’s ignorance of the infinite structure—namely, permanence. The uninstructed worldling confuses the notion of infinity (no beginning, no end) with the notion of eternity, or rather identifies the two. In this way, a present experience is regarded as eternal or permanent. What a puthujjana does not see is that eternity implies infinity, but the infinity does not imply eternity.[7] Because of the nescience in regard to this, the puthujjana’s experience of infinity assumes permanence. In other words, his citta is regarded as permanent; he regards his Self as permanent. If one would be able to see the infinity without eternity, or even to see it as impermanent, the notion of Self, and everything else that depended upon it, (which required the notion of permanence), would cease without a remainder. Knowing infinity as something present (i.e. arisen) but impermanent (for the very reason that it has arisen on its own accord), clears the mind of any obstructions, any superimposed interferences with the infinite structure. Hence it is said that the arahant’s mind is immeasurable.[8] His citta has been developed to the structurally more fundamental state, and it is because this state was always possible (but not actual)[9] that transcending the obstructions was feasible. In other words, if one’s mind was inherently ignorant—i.e. avijjā structurally preceded any experience—arahantship would not be possible. (See footnote [5] above).[10]

Ñāṇavīra Thera took sabbatopabhaṃ to be sabbato-apahaṃ (from apahoti, a+pahoti), in which case this compound would be synonymous with anidassanaṃ, ‘non-indicative’ or ‘not-producing'(Self). (Cf. Ñāṇavīra Thera—Clearing the Path (2010), ‘Note on Paṭiccasamuppāda’, footnote j, p.28). Whether he was right or wrong in reading it like this, it is clear here that either way the context is scarcely affected—the infinity of consciousness does not indicate Self, does not produce Self, and it is fundamentally lucid, radiant, and unobstructed. [back]

Cf. MN 38. [back]

This also indicates that the states of ‘boundlessness’, ‘infinity’ and similar that are mentioned in the Suttas are not exclusively reserved for “meditation attainments”, as they are commonly regarded. [back]

Cf. “There is just this body and name-and-form externally…”—SN 12.19. [back]

“Craving, however, is a gratuitous (though beginningless) parasite on the intentional structure described here, and its necessity is not to be deduced from the necessity of intention in all experience. Intention does not imply craving—a hard thing to understand! But if intention did imply craving, arahatta would be out of the question, and there would be no escape.”—Ñāṇavīra Thera, op. cit., footnote f, p. 56. [back]

Cf. MN 44. [back]

The reader might notice that Ñāṇavīra Thera in ‘Fundamental Structure’ (op.cit. p. 107) refers to the endurance of a thing as ‘eternal’. This structural ‘eternity’ is what is meant here by ‘infinity’. It is just how one decides to designate these terms. If we were to choose the term ‘eternal’ to describe the property of the structure, we would additionally have to qualify it by saying: “A thing endures for ever. A thing is eternal… until it ceases.” I, personally, prefer ‘infinite’ so that the distinction between the inherent nature of the arisen experience (infinity) becomes apparent from the puthujjana’s appropriation of it (eternity). [back]

Cf. AN 3.115 & SN 35.202. [back]

Cf. nibbānadhātu [back]

For these very reasons the Buddha was able to “rediscover” the path which lay there. For more cf. SN 12.65. [back]

Not Perceiving the Feeling (Notes on MN 43)

[source]

Friend, feeling and perception and consciousness-these things are associated, not disassociated. It is not possible to separate them and by separating them point out the difference [between them]. What one feels, that one perceives. What one perceives, that one cognizes. Therefore, these things are associated not disassociated. It is not possible to separate them and by separating them point out the difference[between them].

– MN 43

The Teaching is for the one who feels. When one thinks “this is what I feel”, that is what one thinks, not what one feels. Feeling cannot be thought, it cannot be perceived. What one perceives is one’s perception, what one feels is one’s feeling.[1] Feeling and perception are simply there, superimposed, independent and different in nature.

“What one feels, that one perceives.”

Thinking that it is the same thing that one feels and simultaneously perceives, means one assumes that [same] thing as independent of that feeling and perception. That thing is.

Thinking that it is a different thing that one feels and simultaneously perceives, means one assumes that [different] thing as independent of that feeling and perception. That thing is.

Thinking that it is both-the-same-and-different thing that one feels and simultaneously perceives, means one assumes that [both-the-same-and-different] thing as independent of that feeling and perception. That thing is.

Thinking that it is neither-the-same-nor-different thing that one feels and simultaneously perceives, means one assumes that [neither-the-same-nor-different] thing as independent of that feeling and perception. That thing is.

Thus, through that assumption, one identifies that thing.

Whether one thinks it is the same, or different, or both or neither, feeling is there, regardless of the perception in regard to it. Thus, a feeling cannot be thought, it can only be felt. A perception cannot be felt, it can only be perceived. One has to learn how to feel, or how to know ‘that because of which’ the feeling is.[2] This means how to discern it from that which perception is. This cannot be done by separating feeling and perception and examining them individually.[3] So how can one do it then?-

By feeling [the feeling]. By perceiving [the perception]. By cognizing [the cognizance].

By cognizing feeling-[while]{.underline}-perceiving.

By understanding cognizing.

By not-conceiving perception.

If the superimposition of these two completely independent simultaneously present domains is understood, the assumption of an independent thing,[4] outside of feeling and perception ceases to be “a bridge” for the two. The ‘thing’ which is being identified (as the same, different, both-the-same-and-different, neither-the-same-nor-different), is that “bridge” and feeling and perception ‘meet’ or ‘come together’ because of it. That thing is assumed to be that which one feels and perceives.[5] In this way, feeling and perception (and consciousness) also come to be identified.[6] Thus, that ‘[assumption of a] thing’ which identifies the unidentifiable [7] feeling and perception makes them manifest in that identity-feeling and perception come to exist. The identity feels, the identity perceives-I feel, I perceive.

One feels pleasure, one feels pain, one feels neither-pain-nor-pleasure.

One perceives blue, one perceives yellow, one perceives red, one perceives white.[8]

One can be aware of what one feels; one can also be aware of what one perceives. Through understanding that because of which one is aware of, one knows the feeling and perception structurally cannot overlap or merge or “be bridged” or identified;[9] This makes the assumption in regard to feeling and perception (as the same, different, both-the-same-and-different, neither-the-same-nor-different),[10] redundant, irrelevant, not worth maintaining. Why? Because it does not and it cannot make any difference to the structural order of things (feeling feels, perception perceives). If it could, the freedom from suffering would not be possible.[11] Fully understanding that whichever way one’s thought (assumption) goes, the feeling cannot be identified as (the same, different, both-the-same-and-different, neither-the-same-nor-different from) perception, leaves that feeling and that perception just standing there-indifferent to each other.[12] [13]

Agreeable perception is assumed to be that which is pleasantly felt;

Disagreeable perception is assumed to be that which is unpleasantly felt;

Neutral perception is assumed to be that which is neutrally felt.

Thus, one thinks it is this sight [14] (sounds, smells…thoughts) that is felt. Because of that feeling one sets upon to ‘affect’ those sights (sounds, smells, …thoughts), sets upon to change them, modify them, adjust them, pursue them, avoid them; one gets entangled in the sights (sounds, smells…thoughts) on account of what one feels when they are . Knowing that feeling is just there-being felt, and perception is just there-being perceived, makes further entanglement impossible, and any entanglement that was there[15] is made redundant, disowned, dropped down, never to picked up again. Why? Because it was structurally impossible to get entangled in the first place, but until one has fully understood that, one’s ‘not-knowing-that-one-cannot-be-entangled’ was one’s entanglement. When one understands that the arisen things cannot structurally relate to each other-feeling feels the feeling, perception perceives the perception[16] –concern becomes impossible or inconceivable-dukkha completely ceases, never to arise again.

Cf. Ñāṇavīra Thera, Clearing the Path, SAÑÑĀ, §2. [back]

Or how to not-conceive ‘that because of which’ perception is. [back]

Thinking it in isolation from the present experience (i.e. from perception and consciousness) would amount to this. Since the separation cannot actually occur (not even in one’s imagination), all one can do is assume that which is different between those three. [back]

The [sense of] independence is the inevitable outcome of the presence of the assumption in one’s experience. It is not therefore accidental that one’s sense of Self is always regarded as an extra-temporal and changeless, i.e. independent (from the rest of the experience). Cf. Ñāṇavīra Thera, op.cit., ATTĀ, §1 and L.147, §3. [back]

Thus, because of this assumption, one feels the thing, not one’s feelings; one perceives the thing, not one’s perception. By doing so one conceives things different to what they are, and when those things change one suffers. [back]

Cf. my essay Determining Determinations. ‘That because of which’ [feeling, perception, consciousness are] is assumed as ‘that which’ feeling, perception, consciousness ‘are’. [back]

“It is not possible to separate them and by separating them point out the difference…“-MN 43. [back]

Cf. MN 43. [back]

Or cross into each other’s domains. [back]

All of these are forms of identity. [back]

Cf. my essay The Infinity of Mind. [back]

By understanding this structural ‘indifference’, one feels indifferent to the whole structure-which is what upekkhā is. [back]

It is the nature of the superimposition that breeds this indifference, since concern is in its nature always in relation to something. [back]

Disagreeable (or agreeable, or neutral) [back]

In the past, or possible in the future, or standing there in the present. [back]

Matter matters, feeling feels, perception perceives, determinations determine, consciousness cognizes. [back]

Resistance and Designation (Notes on DN 15)

[source]

Nāmarūpapaccayā phasso’ti iti kho panetaṃ vuttaṃ, tadānanda, imināpetaṃ pariyāyena veditabbaṃ, yathā nāmarūpapaccayā phasso. Yehi, Ānanda, ākārehi yehi liṅgehi yehi nimittehi yehi uddesehi nāmakā-yassa paññatti hoti, tesu ākāresu tesu liṅgesu tesu nimittesu tesu uddesesu asati api nu kho rūpakāye adhivacanasamphasso paññāyethā ti?

No hetaṃ, bhante.

Yehi, Ānanda, ākārehi yehi liṅgehi yehi nimittehi yehi uddesehi rūpakāyassa paññatti hoti, tesu ākāresu tesu ākāresu tesu liṅgesu tesu nimittesu tesu uddesesu tesu uddesesu asati, api nu kho nāmakāye paṭighasamphasso paññāyethā ti?

No hetaṃ, bhante.

Yehi, Ānanda, ākārehi yehi liṅgehi yehi nimittehi yehi uddesehi nāmakāyassa ca rūpakāyassa ca paññatti hoti, tesu ākāresu tesu ākāresu tesu liṅgesu tesu nimittesu tesu uddesesu tesu uddesesu asati, api nu kho adhivacanasamphasso vā paṭighasamphasso vā paññāyethā ti?

No hetaṃ, bhante.

Yehi, Ānanda, ākārehi yehi liṅgehi yehi nimittehi yehi uddesehi nāma-rūpassa paññatti hoti, tesu ākāresu tesu ākāresu tesu liṅgesu tesu nimittesu tesu uddesesu tesu uddesesu asati, api nu kho phasso paññā-yethā ti?

No hetaṃ, bhante.

Tasmātihānanda, eseva hetu etaṃ nidānaṃ esa samudayo esa paccayo phassassa, yadidaṃ nāmarūpaṃ.

"‘With name-&-matter as condition, contact’, so it was said: how it is, Ānanda, that with name-&-matter as condition there is contact should be seen in this manner. Those tokens, Ānanda, those marks, those signs, those indications by which the name-body is described,—they being absent, would designation-contact be manifest in the matter-body?

-No indeed, lord.

-Those tokens, Ānanda, those marks, those signs, those indications by which the matter-body is described,—they being absent, would resistance-contact be manifest in the name-body?

-No indeed, lord.

-Those tokens, Ānanda, those marks, those signs, those indications by which the name-body and the matter-body are described,—they being absent, would either designation-contact or resistance-contact be manifest?

-No indeed, lord.

-Those tokens, Ānanda, those marks, those signs, those indications by which name-&-matter is described,—they being absent, would contact be manifest?

-No indeed, lord.

-Therefore, Ānanda, just this is the reason, this is the occasion, this is the arising, this is the condition of contact, that is to say name-&-matter."

1. ‘Matter’ is required for ‘name’ to be present. If there would not be that which is ‘named’, ‘name’ would not be able to arise. If on the other hand, ‘name’ is absent, ‘matter’ would simply be inconceivable. Thus, there is no ‘name’ without ‘matter’ and there is no ‘matter’ without ‘name’, hence-name-&-matter. In this way ‘name’ designates the resistance, and ‘matter’ resists the designation. Without ‘name'(-body), there would not be any designation manifested in ‘matter'(-body), but without ‘matter'(-body), there would not be any resistance manifested in the ‘name'(-body). It is these respective manifestations of ‘designation’ and ‘resistance’ that are puthujjana’s problem.

2. With name-&-matter, he assumes that it is this ‘matter’ that is designated. Through that assumption, designation manifests in that matter body[1]. In this way one’s ‘matter’ is designated-one is contacted.

With name-&-matter, he assumes that it is this ‘name’ that is resisted. Through that assumption, resistance manifests in that name-body. In this way one’s ‘name’ is resisted-one is contacted.

He assumes that it is *this* 'matter' that is designated.

He assumes it is the same ‘matter’ that is designated and is the condition for ‘name’; he assumes it is a different ‘matter’ that is designated and is the condition for ‘name’; He assumes it is both-same-&-different matter that is designated and is the condition for ‘name’; He assumes it is neither-same-nor-different ‘matter’ that is designated and is the condition for ‘name’. Either way-the assumption is there.

That which resists him he designates as the same, different, both-same-&-different, or neither same-nor-different, as that because of which ‘name’ is there. The designation manifests in this ‘matter’.[2]

Thus, he designates (contacts) his resistance. Contact is there.

He assumes that it is *this* 'name' that is resisted.

He assumes it is the same ‘name’ that is resisted and is the condition for ‘matter’; He assumes it is a different ‘name’ that is resisted and is the condition for ‘matter’; He assumes it is both-same-&-different ‘name’ that is resisted and is the condition for ‘matter’; He assumes it is neither-same-nor-different ‘name’ that is resisted and is the condition for ‘matter’; Either way-the assumption is there.

That which is designated he resists as the same, different, both-same-&-different, or neither same-nor-different, as that because of which ‘matter’ is there. The resistance manifests in this ‘name’.[3]

Thus, he resists (contacts) his designation. Contact is there.

3. Cf. Mūḷapariyāya Sutta, MN 1:

Pathaviṃ pathavito sañjānāti; pathaviṃ pathavito saññatvā pathaviṃ maññati, pathaviyā maññati, pathavito maññati, pathaviṃ meti maññati, pathaviṃ abhinandati. taṃ kissa hetu? `apariññātaṃ tassā’ti vadāmi.

“From earth, he has a percept of earth; having had from earth a percept, he conceives [that to be] earth, he conceives [that to be] in earth, he conceives [that to be] out of earth, he conceives earth as ‘mine’, he delights earth. Why is that? He has not fully understood it, I say…”

What a puthujjana has to realise is that regardless of what he perceives, it is always his perception that is perceived. Whether it is ‘earth’, ‘water’, ‘fire’, ‘air’ or any other thing that MN 1 mentions, all one will ever perceive (puthujjana and arahant alike) is one’s own perception of that ‘matter’.[4] This is saying nothing else than ‘matter’ is and will always be outside of one’s reach, outside of that which has appeared.[5] Perception is that which is perceived, but perception would not be possible if there is no matter to be perceived; on the other hand matter would be inconceivable if perception was indiscernible. If one thinks “it is because of the matter, that perception is there”, that thought is perceived, which means that that which is ‘matter’ in that thought is also perceived. But since it is only perception that can be perceived, that ‘matter’ which is perceived in that thought, cannot be that ‘matter’ which cannot be perceived, since it is perceived. In this way, from ‘matter’, a puthujjana has a percept of ‘matter’, which he conceives to be that same ‘matter’ because of which there is a percept of matter. Or he conceives it to be different ‘matter’ because of which there is a percept of matter. Or he conceives it to be both-same &-different ‘matter’ because of which there is a percept of matter. Or he conceives it to be neither-same-nor-different ‘matter’ because of which there is a percept of matter. Either way ‘matter’ is conceived. He becomes responsible for the manifestation of the conceiving of that ‘matter’, he “makes” that ‘matter’ exist.[6] That “creation” is his-thus it is ‘my’ ‘matter’.[7] But, since that ‘my matter’ is conceived as that ‘matter’ because of which there is a percept of matter, then that percept[ion] too becomes ‘my perception’.[8] The same goes for one’s feelings and intentions. They are all conceived as mine. Since the puthujjana’s whole experience is his, he thinks he himself is-the view of Self exists.[9]

4. When consciousness does not indicate any ‘me’ or ‘mine’, that ‘matter’ because of which there is a percept of matter, does not manifest itself in that perception (or feeling, or intention)-it does not manifest itself in ‘name’. Thus, in perception there is only perception, i.e. in the seen there is only that which is seen, namely-the seen (and so on for all the senses).[10] One ceases to “perceive ‘matter”’; one knows[11] such a thing is impossible or inconceivable,[12] one simply understands[13]: there is matter, there is perception (or feeling, or intention), there is (non-indicative) consciousness. One understands-there are five “heaps”.[14] Since one understands them, one ceases to assume them. With the cessation of assumption, that which they were assumed to be, ceases-bhava comes to an end.

Upādānapaccayā bhavo. [back]

‘Name’ assumes existence in ‘matter’-‘name’ exists. [back]

‘Matter’ finds footing in ‘name’-‘matter’ exists.Cf. DN 11. [back]

“It would be as wrong to say ‘a feeling is perceived’ as it would ‘a percept is felt’ (which mix up saññā and vedanā); but it is quite in order to say ‘a feeling, a percept, (that is, a felt thing, a perceived thing) is cognized’, which simply means that a feeling or a percept is present (as, indeed, they both are in all experience—see Majjhima v,3 (M.i,293)). Strictly speaking, then, what is cognized is nāmarūpa, whereas what is perceived (or felt) is saññā (or vedanā), i.e. only nāma. This distinction can be shown grammatically. Vijānāti, to cognize, is active voice in sense (taking an objective accusative): consciousness cognizes a phenomenon (nāmarūpa); consciousness is always consciousness of something. Sañjānāti, to perceive, (or vediyati, to feel) is middle voice in sense (taking a cognate accusative): perception perceives [a percept] (or feeling feels [a feeling]). Thus we should say ‘a blue thing (= a blueness), a painful thing (= a pain), is cognized’, but ‘blue is perceived’ and ‘pain is felt’. (In the Suttas generally, due allowance is to be made for the elasticity in the common usage of words. But in certain passages, and also in one’s finer thinking, stricter definition may be required.)”-Ñāṇavīra Thera, Clearing the Path, 2010, p. 92. [back]

Cf. Ñāṇavīra Thera, Seeking The Path, 2010, p. 40, §§17-18: “[Four mahābhutā]…will always be just below our feet.” [back]

Thus, ‘matter’ can never be perceived, but it can “find footing” in that which is perceived (or felt, or intended). [back]

He delights in his own creation, because it is his own creation. [back]

If one is not to conceive that ‘matter’ because of which there is a percept of matter, one would not conceive oneself as that because of which there is a perceiver and conceiver of the world. Cf. SN 35.116: The eye… ear… nose… tongue… body… mind… is that in the world by which one is a perceiver and conceiver of the world. Also, cf. Ñāṇavīra Thera, op.cit. p. 298: And when shall we ‘not be that by which’? … the Buddha tells us: it is when, for us, in the seen there shall be just the seen, and so with the heard, the sensed, and the cognized. And when in the seen is there just the seen? When the seen is no longer seen as ‘mine’ (etaṃ mama) or as ‘I’ (eso’ham asmi) or as ‘my self’ (eso me attā): in brief, when there is no longer, in connexion with the senses, the conceit ‘I am’, by which ‘I am a conceiver of the world’. [back]

That’s how the sense of the ‘mine’ leads to the sense of ‘Self’. [back]

Cf. Bāhiya Sutta, Ud. 10/8. [back]

“Wisdom is to be developed…“-MN 43. [back]

If it were fundamentally subject to one’s conceivings, freedom from conceivings would not be possible. Cf. my. [back]

“…consciousness is to be understood”.-MN 43. [back]

Simultaneous, superimposed, utterly indifferent to each other. [back]

Determining Determinations

[source]

1. Feeling, perception and consciousness are always there together.[1] It is impossible to have them arising independently and on their own; when there is one, the other two are present as well. They do not pass into each other’s domain[2]: one feels one’s feeling, one perceives one’s perception, one cognizes one’s cognizance. Assuming that it is the same thing that one feels, perceives and cognizes, or assuming that it is a different thing that one feels, perceives, and cognizes, or both-the-same-&-different thing that one feels, perceives, and cognizes, or neither-the-same-nor-different thing that one feels, perceives, and cognizes, means that assumed thing is there-it exists. One conceives it through one’s feeling, one’s perception, and one’s cognizance. One conceives that thing because of which feeling, perception and cognizance are there, as that thing because of which feeling, perception and cognizance are there. But since all one can ever feel is one’s feeling; all one can ever perceive is one’s perception; all one can ever cognize is one’s cognizance-that thing which is conceived as that because of which feeling, perception and cognizance are there, will have to be either a feeling, a perception or a cognizance, and as such cannot be that because of which feeling, perception and cognizance are there.[3] By conceiving a feeling, or a perception, or a cognizance as that because of which feeling, perception and cognizance are there, one assumes that feeling, or perception, or cognizance, existing independently of feeling, perception and cognizance, as that because of which feeling, perception and cognizance are there. Thus, that because of which feeling, perception and cognizance are there, manifests in that feeling, perception or cognizance which are assumed [to be]{.underline} that because of which feeling, perception and cognizance are there. Thus, that because of which feeling, perception and cognizance are there, manifests in that being-it exists.

2. That because of which feeling, perception and cognizance are there, is that which is a necessary condition for feeling, perception and cognizance that are there, because without it, that feeling, perception and cognizance would not be there. As a necessary condition, that because of which feeling, perception and cognizance are there, is thus that by which feeling, perception and cognizance are determined. But since through the assumption, that by which feeling, perception and cognizance are determined, manifests as feeling, perception, or cognizance because of which that feeling, perception and cognizance are there, that feeling, perception and cognizance are determined [as that by which]{.underline} feeling, perception and cognizance are determined.[4] Thus, through not knowing that one can only feel one’s feelings, perceive one’s perception, cognize one’s cognizance,[5] one determines that by which one’s feeling, perception and cognizance are determined, as a feeling, a perception or a cognizance. Through that lack of knowledge, determinations are manifested-avijjāpaccayā saṅkārā.

3. One determines one’s determinations through assuming that because of which determinations are there.

But that because of which determinations are there cannot be that which is determined by those determinations, since all one can determine are one’s determination, not that because of which those determinations are there. Since determinations cannot determine that because of which determinations are there, that because of which determinations are there is that which is non-determinable-it is undetermined. If that because of which the determinations are there was to be determined, then the escape from determinations would not be possible.[6]

One can know that that because of which determinations are there cannot be determined.

Without knowing that knowing, one’s knowledge of that because of which determinations are there, determines that because of which determinations are there, as that because of which determinations are there.[7]

Since that because of which determinations are there cannot fundamentally be determined, one’s knowledge that determines that because of which determinations are there, leads to ‘assuming’ that because of which determinations are there as that because of which determinations are there.

And since that assumption is then there, that which is determined as that because of which determinations are there, is there too, as that assumed determination because of which determinations are there-it is manifested, it exists.

One can know that that because of which determinations are there cannot be determined.

By knowing that knowing,[8] one’s knowledge of that because of which determinations are there, does not determine that because of which determinations are there,[9] as that because of which determinations are there.

Since that because of which determinations are there cannot fundamentally be determined,[10] one’s knowledge that does not determine that because of which determinations are there does not lead to ‘assuming’ that because of which determinations are there as that because of which determinations are there.

And since that assumption is then not there, that which is determined as that because of which determinations are there, is not there either, as that assumed determination because of which determinations are there-it is not manifested, it does not exist.[11] [12] [13]

Cf. MN 43. [back]

Cf. Notes on DN 15. [back]

Now is probably the time to mention that none of this, nor paragraphs to follow, can be grasped intellectually by the reader. Things that are described here are not to be made sense of in a rationally or philosophically satisfying way, but to be seen in a certain order that they arise in one’s experience. Hence the deliberate repetitive style which aligns things in the order they are to be understood (which is also the reason why the Suttas are in that form). Also, refraining from a too particular and established terminology was intentional, since that would most likely lead a reader to assume that he already knows what those terms refer to. [back]

Cf. Khanda Saṃyutta viii,7. [back]

And not that because of which feeling, perception and cognizance are there. [back]

“There is, monks, (a) non-born, non-become, non-made, non determined. If, monks, there were not that non-born, non-become, non-made, non-determined, an escape from (the) born, become, made, determined would not be discernible. But, because there is (a) non-born, non-become, non-made, non-determined escape from (the) born, become, made, determined is discernible.”—Nibbāna Sutta, Ud. 8/3. the structure of the experience fundamentally be appropriated, freedom from the appropriation is possible. [back]

“From nibbāna, he has a percept of nibbāna; having known nibbāna from nibbāna, he conceives nibbāna, he conceives in nibbāna, he conceives out of nibbāna, he conceives ‘My’ nibbāna, he delights nibbāna. Why is that? He has not fully understood it, I say.”—MN 1. Also cf. MN 102, [237]. [back]

One knows that whether one intends toward, away, both or neither, in regard to that because of which intentions are there, that because of which intentions are there remains there, regardless of the intention in regard to it. By understanding that it is fundamentally inaccessible to one’s intentions, one ceases to crave towards it with those intentions, one ceases to assume it through those intentions, since neither intentions nor that which directly stands upon them, namely-one’s assumption-could access it. And one knows that. [‘Ignorant intentions’ are simply craving, which leads to ‘assumption’-taṇhapaccayā upādāna. Cf. Ñāṇavīra Thera, op.cit., p.56, footnote f.: “Intention does not imply craving-a hard thing to understand!”]). [back]

Does not “stand for it” in one’s experience, does not “represent it”, does not “manifest it”. [back]

Cannot be ‘accessed’ by it. [back]

The assumption is made redundant. [back]

If one thinks “there is that because of which intentions are there, which is inaccessible to those intentions”, that thought ‘stands for’ that because of which intentions are there, and through that thought one assumes access to that inaccessible-inaccessible exists. If one knows that regardless of what a thought or intention stand for, it can never “step outside” of its nature-one can only think one’s thoughts (perception perceived) or intend one’s intentions, not that because of which that thought/intention are there-one ceases to assume that which that intention stands for, because of which intention is there. Thus, intention remains, while “attempts to access” fade away, since one sees them as pointless and loses interest in them. When those “attempts” are thoroughly subdued, ‘the assumption’ of that which was assumed “accessible” (through those very attempts) disappears too, never to return. [back]

The only reason why assumption can be made redundant, is because it was redundant in the first place. Not knowing that it was redundant, makes it necessary, until it ceases to be so. And the reason why assumption presents itself as necessary is because it assumes that which is necessary in one’s experience, namely-the five aggregates. Thus, the five aggregates, which are necessary in one’s experience, come to exist, through the assuming of them as that which is necessary in one’s experience. But since they are necessary in one’s experience, assuming them as necessary in one’s experience is not necessary. But until one knows that, that assumption will exist. [back]

Notes on Meditaion

[source pdf] [external link]

1. Mindfulness of breathing, bhikkhus, developed and repeatedly practised, is of great fruit, of great benefit; mindfulness of breathing, bhikkhus, developed and repeatedly practised, perfects the four foundations of mindfulness; the four foundations of mindfulness, developed and repeatedly practised, perfect the seven enlightenment factors; the seven enlightenment factors, developed and repeatedly practised, perfect knowledge and freedom…

2. Here, bhikkhus, a bhikkhu, gone to the forest, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty place, sits down; having folded his legs crosswise, set his body erect, established mindfulness in front of him, ever mindful he breathes in, mindful he breathes out.

3. Breathing in long, he knows, ‘I breathe in long’; or breathing out long, he knows, ‘I breathe out long.’

4. Breathing in short, he knows, ‘I breathe in short’; or breathing out short, he knows, ‘I breathe out short.’

5. ‘Experiencing the whole body, I shall breathe in,’ he trains himself thus; ‘experiencing the whole body, I shall breathe out,’ he trains himself thus.

6. ‘Calming the bodily determination, I shall breathe in,’ he trains himself thus; ‘calming the bodily determination, I shall breathe out,’ he trains himself thus…

– Ānāpānasati Sutta (MN 118)

1. The practice of ānāpānasati or mindfulness of breathing represents a phenomenological exercise in developing the principle of simultaneity (akālikā dhamma). This is accomplished by the sufficient establishing of mindfulness and knowledge of what one is supposed to do and discern.[1] It is an exercise because it requires one actively engaging in and being aware of the act of breathing, and it develops the principle of simultaneity because while one is actively breathing, one is aware of one’s actions (body, feelings, and thoughts). These are two different, simultaneously present things: the physical or bodily act of breathing, and the mental reflexive thoughts of one doing that very act. One is not supposed to be favoured on account of the other; a person should not be overdoing the breathing (i.e. turning it into a forceful breathing exercise) nor should he be underdoing it (i.e. forgetting about the act of breathing that is being performed, and letting it happen unawares). In the same sense one should not overthink one’s thinking (i.e. get lost in thought). The point is to mindfully breathe while remaining fully aware of oneself-mindfully-breathing, or – to put it simply – to remain aware of the present phenomenon of “I am breathing.”

2. Breathing is an intentional action, not a habit, and there is volition involved in every single breath a person takes. The reason why most people think breathing is an automated process is because they are almost never aware of it. Thus the intentional side of the breath remains obscured.[2] By being an act (kamma), it has potential, if understood as such, to reveal the nature of all acts (present, future and past), of everything one has ever intentionally done and planning to do. By being an intentional act, breathing shares the same universal nature as all good and evil actions in this world. The reason why breathing is such a suitable act for the practice of mindfulness[3] is because it is an immediately neutral action, there is no actual good or bad involved in it. Thus, although it shares the same nature as all these other more “kammically” (and consequentially) engaging acts, there are no future results involved that would pertain to oneself and others. The merit of an in-breath ceases with an out-breath.

3. As we see from the opening excerpt, by “training oneself thus…,” a monk develops mindfulness of both immediate and possible action (kamma): “I breathe in/out (thus)…,” and “(thus) I shall breathe in/out….” This kind of mindfulness when developed leaves nothing out, and one is simply, yet steadily, becoming more aware of the nature of action in general while that very action is actually present. Ultimately of course, this leads to the full transparency of that “I”, in that experience of breathing as a whole, and it's utterly redundant nature that is being gratuitously assumed.[4] This nature, if mindfulness pursued to the extent necessary,[5] can eventually be completely understood and the gratuitous “I” destroyed. This, however, should not be taken in a sense that the phenomenon of “I” would disappear like it was never there, but in a sense that that “I” will cease to be “me” and “mine”. It will remain just standing there, hollow and dry.

4. The reason why it is recommended that one should sit when exercising mindfulness of breathing is because such a posture offers the least distractions to one’s mind. When seated, one will not be engaging in any other action different from breathing (and passively sitting of course). So, the only thing that one is going to be doing is breathing. In this way it can be understood that sitting is the most optimal posture to have, so that one wouldn’t be wasting any effort. Consequently, with the further development of the discernment of the simultaneously present phenomena, and with the strengthening of mindfulness, one can more freely assume other postures and not remain confined to sitting alone. Furthermore, even engaging in other acts, for example: “while breathing, I am sweeping the floor,” will not be a distraction for one’s mindfulness in any way. In this particular instance, one’s mindfulness and discernment is divided, or shared by, two simultaneously present actions (sweeping and breathing), while one is also simultaneously aware of that thing as a whole. And this division can continue as far as the strength of one’s mindfulness allows, though there is no particular benefit and reason in pushing it.

5. Sometimes people assume that in ānāpānasati one is mindful of the “body of breath,” as opposed to just one’s (experience of) body.[6] This rendering comes from the confusion and lack of phenomenological insight into the nature of the (appearing) body. If one is to understand that whether it is the ordinary experience of one’s body in everyday existence, or an unusual one resulting from the new practice of concentration, or even a strange sense of lightness of one’s body on drugs, in phenomenological terms – body is just there. Thus, again, regardless of the particular way one’s body presents itself, it is the phenomenon of the body that is present, and that’s what one should be concerned with. So, when practising mindfulness of breathing, one actually devotes direct attention to the ‘act of breathing,’ that body (or that strange-sense-of-body) that emerges as a phenomenon, peripherally, is that which is the body, in that experience right then and there. In this way one experiences one’s body through an act of breathing, which is why the Buddha said that body, as one of the foundations of mindfulness, is brought to fulfillment in the practice of ānāpānasati.[7]

By being able to see peripherally that which appears as peripheral, but simultaneously present, one does not conceive it. It is the intention in regard to the peripheral,[8] which tends to make things actual[9] that carries appropriation. If one succeeds in leaving it peripheral (i.e. the way it has arisen), one is practicing mindfulness correctly. The tendency towards ‘conceivings’ will slowly fade when the mindfulness reaches the necessary extent. Again, knowledge of what the conceiving is (i.e. not understanding the phenomenon of simultaneously and dependently present and leaving it as such), is an absolute requirement, because without it this whole practice won’t bear fruits of any fundamental importance. However, even a puthujjana, by trying to understand what the correct practice of mindfulness is, might actually understand it, and then cease to be a puthujjana, so this whole practice should be encouraged regardless.[10]

6. The contemporary Buddhist outlook usually equates the practice of ānāpānasati with the practice of jhānas, and if not regarded as the same, it is too often thought that by practicing ānāpānasati one will by default “enter” a jhāna. I suspect this assumption stems from the commentarial times, whereby various meditation techniques, that revolve around the idea of the mindfulness of breathing, were concocted and advertised as something that would directly lead to the experience of jhānas.[11]

Jhānas are the establishments of mind, and as such they are to be developed upon the sufficient degree of mindfulness, which in return can be established upon various different things, ānāpānasati being one of them.[12] Thus, it should be clear, that the practice of jhāna is a fundamentally different practice from ānāpānasati. While ānāpānasati shares a nature of the phenomenological exercise of one’s actions in regard to body, feelings, mind and thoughts, jhāna is less of that, but more of an establishment of one’s mind upon a certain way of attending to things (in this case upon a phenomenological surmounting of the sensual domain), and the discernment involved therein. In other words, by understanding what jhāna is, one enters it,[13] not by performing a set of prescribed motions that somehow make it “happen” to one.

Obviously, one can develop and establish an unwavering mindfulness through the practice of ānāpānasati, and once established one could change one’s outlook and with such mindfulness recognize the extent of sensuality, as a phenomenon, and what exactly it entails, and by doing so step outside of it, so to speak. In this way one would enter the first jhāna, where that mindfulness would remain fully established and can be developed even further.[14] It is clear here that it is not that ānāpānasati in itself took one automatically into a jhāna, but that the change of attending to things did,[15] once the mindfulness was strong enough. Furthermore, jhāna is not taught as a goal in itself, as Kāyagatāsati Sutta (MN 119) tells us, but as one of the forms that can bring one’s mindfulness to the necessary fulfillment.

So, in order for any of these paragraphs to be intelligible, one will have to abandon the notions of “meditation techniques' and all the contemporary ideas of the practice of concentration, which is usually taught at the expense of mindfulness and with underlying wrong views (such as mystical absorptions and novelty experiences that then become a measure of one’s “success”). When a person hears the term ānāpānasati, he will be better o thinking “development of mindfulness” – the same mindfulness that he has to varying extents in his day-to-day experiences.

7. “Meditation techniques” are usually sets of fairly random motions and performances, idiosyncratic to the particular meditation teacher, that require one to fol ow certain prescribed steps which if performed correctly, and with some luck, will make one experience “something”. Often, in return, that same teacher would have to “interpret” back these experiences for one.

To put it bluntly: if one needs to be told by another what the significance of one’s experience was, this means one has not understood it by oneself. It means one is still concerned with the particular aspects (i.e. the random contents) of one’s meditation experience, and one fails to see the general nature of it all. As a result, any external interpretation is regarded as an explanation, which means that phenomenology remains buried deep down under layers of preconceived ideas and assumptions. This holds true even more when it comes to the idea of “attainments”, which are also regarded as experiences that “happen” to one, almost against one’s will and as a result of “a very good technique” one has employed. There is a concealed irony there that escapes such people, because if one needs to be “confirmed” a sotāpanna, for example, by one’s teacher, this means one doesn’t know that one actually is a sotāpanna, which means that one can still doubt it, which in return means that one is not freed from the fetter of doubt, i.e. actually not a sotāpanna. The irony is further amplified if the teacher goes ahead and “confirms' one. If one is to actually understand what “being free from doubt” (and the other two fetters, characteristic of the sotāpanna) is, one would realize how non-applicable any external affirmation or denial is.[16]

How obstructive to phenomenology (i.e. mindfulness) this whole way of practising is, can be seen from the nature of understanding. One understands things when one understands them, when the knowledge in regard to the nature of an arisen thing is there, and not when one successfully goes through a set of methods and observances that relies on an almost mechanical set of motions one has to perform attentively. Any bodily act and any act that pertains to the bodily domain (such as the celebrated and misguided notion of “sensations”[17] which involve observing different parts and aspects of one’s body) is simply irrelevant for the discerning of the nature of an arisen phenomenon.[18] It is misleading and obstructive, because it is impossible to engage in a technique without the implicit belief that a set of motions, that the chosen technique consists of, performed in a particular mechanical order, will somehow, by itself, reveal the nature of things. By holding this belief and faith in a technique, one will not be trying to understand things, and by not making attempts toward the understanding, one will definitely remain devoid of it.

One sees things correctly – as phenomena – by understanding what the phenomenon is, and there is no technique that can make this magically occur. Thus, the closest to what one should do in order to obtain understanding is: trying to understand. For as long as a person is attempting to understand and see the nature of an arisen thing, that person might actually succeed in it, for it is certain that understanding cannot occur in someone who is not trying to understand. Incidentally (or not), there is never any mention of meditation techniques in the Suttas, but ‘understanding’ and ‘discernment’, as a way to reach the final freedom from suffering, is described and referred to countless times.

When one looks at the experience mindfully, it becomes apparent that regardless of the content of the particular experience, the nature of experience is present. So, whether it is the experience of “impatiently-waiting-for-a-bus,” or the experience of tiredness after a physical exertion, or strange and novel experience of a powerful light that occurred in front of me while meditating on a seven-day technique-based meditation retreat, all I should be concerned about is that an experience is there and as such it needs to be understood.[19] This means that investing effort into meditation techniques is fundamentally a waste of time if one is concerned with understanding the Dhamma, and the most one can accomplish is relaxation, a sense of peace coming from withdrawal from the habitual world of senses, or – worse – fortification of the wrong views based on a misinterpretation of the nature of the novelty experiences. Either way, the results of any technique one might engage in, will remain worldly, and will draw its power from a temporary change of one’s environment, one’s usual way of regarding things. In any case, the “benefits” and “helpfulness” of a chosen technique will simply share the nature of a phenomenon of novelty that one is experiencing. As such, it means it will run out, and one will have to either do it harder, or change the technique.

If people attend meditation retreats as a form of a temporary escape from the busy and oppressing world, by all means they should do it, as often as they can. However, rather than engaging in a practice of a technique and “sensation watching,” they would be better o using their quiet time in trying to understand the nature of things according to the way the Buddha described it, whether sitting, walking or lying down. For it is that “nature” which the Dhamma means and refers to, and anything that is not dealing with this, or anything that is obscuring that very nature (i.e. phenomena) of things, consequently is not the Dhamma, no matter how “helpful” and “useful” it might be.[20] In different words, one’s experience is phenomenological (i.e. the five aggregates are all simultaneously present in their respective domains), and this means that nature of things comes first,[21] before anything one does based on that nature. Doing a technique in order to practice the Dhamma (i.e. see the nature of things) is like exiting the house, so as to be in it. It’s a contradiction in terms.

8. In the first establishment of mind, the first jhāna, the appropriation of the bodily action (intention) ceases. This is accomplished when that thought, which in ordinary experience stands for that which is the body (and anything originating from it) is seen in its phenomenological nature, i.e. as thought,[22] When the mind is thus established upon the signs and characteristics of one’s thought, as an arisen thing, that thought is recognized as being indifferent[23] to anything other than itself, such as body and matter.[24] Through that very indifference, the thought, even if it thinks about the body and anything bodily, ceases to stand for ‘that’ which is the body (rūpa). This is why the first jhāna is primarily characterized by thinking-and-pondering (vittakavicāra) and it is also why the sensual domain (i.e. domain that is pertaining to the body) has been surmounted. The result of this cessation is the subsiding of speech – the physical, bodily aspect of it. By dropping the appropriation of the bodily intention, through the surmounting of its whole domain, one clearly sees the whole body as an independent thing, just sitting there, already given. Even if one is to make a bodily intention, one would see that intention too, as something that is inevitably and inseparably confined to the bodily domain and as such: as something that can never be “mine”. This is why the first establishment of mind is also sufficient for the final knowledge.[25]

Furthermore, it is because of this very principle of thought ceasing to ‘stand for’ that which is the body, that the jhānas are wholesome in themselves, even if not accompanied by understanding. By “ceasing to stand for” the wrong order of the experience is reversed, and the structurally independent, simultaneously present and indifferent to each other individual domains of the aggregates are experienced as they are, without the distortion introduced by assumption in regard to them. This is why the Buddha praised the practice of jhāna, because if the person develops them correctly, even as a puthujjana, he would require very little instruction in order to understand things and remove all conceivings and avijjā.

Which is why in order to correctly do any of the practices found in the Suttas, one needs the right view first. [back]

Cf. Ñāṇavīra Thera, Clearing the Path, p. 195. [back]

As recommended in SN 54:9. [back]

Whether it is “I am breathing in,” or “I shall breathe in,” through mindful repetition the “I” begins to stand out, so to speak, and when paired with understanding, the more it “stands out,” the less it is mine. [back]

Cf. MN 10. [back]

This should not be mistaken as “sensations”. See below. [back]

The same principle applies to the other foundations, namely – feelings, mind and thoughts. [back]

That which is simultaneously present, but “less” there, less actual. [back]

Or: “Right in front of us”; to “take them up.” [back]

This doesn’t mean that any (i.e. fall sorts of contradictory) practice of meditation is being endorsed here. This is because, for a puthujjana, no matter how much effort he makes, if the practice he has chosen or been given is inherently wrong, no right results can come from it. One does not accidentally become sotāpanna, it doesn’t “happen to one” as a blessing. One builds it up, develops it and attains it through “manly efforts,” as the Suttas often say, and because it was not given to one, it cannot be taken away. [back]

Which inevitably acquired countless mystical connotations that they maintain to this day. [back]

Cf. SN 54:8. [back]

Cf. SN 40:1. [back]

Cf. MN 119. [back]

Cf. SN 54:8. [back]

Cf. Sn 1:3,21 (verse 55). [back]

Cf. Ñāṇavīra Thera, Clearing the Path, p. 75. [back]

In other words, it is impossible to perform an action which in and by itself would be able to overcome the nature of action, which is the whole point of the Buddhist practice: overcoming kamma. Through action, good or bad or neutral, all one accomplishes is the maintenance of the nature of action: by acting, one remains bound by action. If this would not be the case, the Buddha and the Dhamma would not be required for the freedom from suffering, and all one would have to do is simply perform certain things and by doing so, automatically reach nibbāna, or even better: all one would have to do is choose to be in nibbāna and one would attain it. [back]

And one also comes to realize that for as long as one is alive, experience is always there, and one doesn’t have to do anything in order for it to be so. And this is where the real purpose of a meditation technique becomes apparent: one is after a particular type of experience (regarded as more desirable and lofty) as a form of replacement or escape from another type of experience (regarded as undesirable and unpleasant). “I want to experience this, I don’t want to experience that (or lack-of-this). Thus, all one is trying to do is experience pleasant by directly displacing unpleasant, i.e. one wants to fulfill one's immediate desire. For as long as one remains concerned and puts value on the particulars of an experience, the nature of it will remain unknown. This is the reason why any meditation of this kind is a meditation that is utterly within the sensual domain and cannot go beyond it, which is what MN 108 (iii, 14) refers to. [back]

People themselves might often struggle to reconcile the nature of meditation techniques with the nature of the Buddha’s Teaching, but they usually end up ignoring this because it feels like the immediate application of a technique is helping them and makes them feel better. The problem with this is that they, as puthujjanas, have no criteria to determine what “helpful” really is. Thus, they just end up following their own feelings and assumptions again, but this time on the pretext of Buddhism and spiritual practice. [back]

One can be ignorant of the phenomenological nature only because that nature is there, present. [back]

Cf. my essay Not Perceiving the Feeling (Meanings, p. 43) where I said that it is the feeling that feels, perception that perceives and thought that thinks (I am paraphrasing). [back]

This is a type of structural indifference and this can be understood in terms of the superimposition of the respective domains of body (matter) and thoughts. Both of these domains are simultaneously present, but they don’t interfere – they are “indifferent” to each other. Furthermore, it is not just that they don’t interfere, it is that they cannot interfere, even if one is to want it. This principle actually applies to the whole experience, namely: the five aggregates. Crossing from one domain into another is structurally inconceivable, but as long as one does not fully understand that, by not-understanding one conceives it. For more on this cf. my essays The Infinity of the Mind and Not Perceiving the Feeling (Meanings, p. 39 and p.43). [back]

And this very indifference was obscured through the assumption of ‘body’ (i.e. matter) in one’s thoughts. Cf. Resistance and Designation (Meanings, p. 47). [back]

“Bhikkhus, I say that the destruction of the taints occurs in dependence on the first jhāna…”

– AN 9:36 [back]

Breathing Towards Death

[source]

Practising the mindfulness of breathing correctly, means practising the mindfulness of death correctly.

The Buddha has offered mindfulness of breathing as a replacement for the practice of mindfulness of death. That was because mindfulness of death pushed some monks over the edge, so to speak. It made them wish for ending of their life before being fully awakened. Yet, it is important to note that mindfulness of breath aims at the same result as mindfulness of death does. That result is dispassion towards the world and life (of sensuality) in general. The mindfulness of breathing was a direct response to the need for rapid dispassion of those committed to its practice. This of course doesn’t mean that mindfulness of death was wrong, but it means that mindfulness of breath is simply less risky. It cannot be stressed enough though – they both aim at the same result.

Furthermore, this applies for any other “meditation” that we find in Suttas. They might sound very different, but their aim is the same: the establishment of mindfulness. Mindfulness to the extent necessary for the discernment of Dhamma. Thus, we can say that if someone’s meditation is not bringing them closer to understanding of sensuality and experience of dispassion – that meditation is wrong.

The breath can end at any given moment, and we wouldn’t be able to do anything about it. Random organ failure, heart attack, lung collapse, none of these things would be accessible to our will power, yet, our entire life (that same “will power”) directly and simultaneously depends on it. For example, if something were to happen to the vital functions of our body, our life would end that very moment. Regardless of where our hopes and intentions were aiming at the time. This recognition can be very unpleasant for an average inauthentic man of the world and it could result in the experience of a tremendous fear and dread. It is the aim of the mindfulness of death to cut through the manifold layers of that inauthenticity. But, as the Buddha has himself seen, it can sometimes be too much to handle; if a person realizes one’s own mortality too fast and is not prepared for it. Hence the mindfulness of breathing comes as a more gradual replacement. A replacement that still, very much, leads in the same direction of recognizing the inherent insecurity of one’s own life. This insecurity manifests through realizing the impermanence of breath, while one mindfully breathes. So, the difference between mindfulness of breath and mindfulness of death is not in its “object”, but in a point of view. (or where the mindfulness is anchored in).

In ‘death meditation’ the point of view is in one’s sense of Self. This is more “personal” approach (which is why it is sharper, quicker, and thus riskier). In ‘breath meditation’ the point of view is placed on the intentional act of breathing. By doing so, one’s sense of Self is not in the direct center of the experience. (as opposed to the thought “I will die”, for example). Either way, one can realize that no matter how volitional an act (of breathing) might be, it is fundamentally rooted away from one’s control. (Control that is the exemplification of one’s sense of Self.). This becomes clear when one recognizes that while breathing, the body (or the lungs, or heart, etc.) could stop working. They could fail. That whole dimension, where the failure would come from, would remain entirely “inaccessible” to one’s intentions and will. No amount of one’s volition would be able to “cross” that threshold of control that is determined by the present body that is simply “able to breath”. (i.e. unobstructed airways, functioning lungs, beating heart, etc.). In simple terms: one’s sense of control, intentions, will, sense of Self, are all bound up with presently arisen functioning body. And the presence of that body is not accessible to one’s will. (If it were so, we wouldn’t be susceptible to illness, aging and death.). Recognition of that lack of access to the fundamental aspects of one’s own life, is the recognition of impermanence. Thus, in mindfulness of breathing, one exposes oneself to the sharp truth of anicca, but without winding oneself up through the anxious contemplation of death.

We can go as far as to say that one’s life is completely rooted outside one’s own sense of control. In other words, one’s ability to exercise will and control, is something that one has no control over. For example: if something random, (an accident or, a disease,) were to simply block the air passages, no amount of intentional breathing would be able to help us. Yet, our whole life would depend on it.

Correctly discerning this, results in the right dispassion. And that means having no desire for either life or death.

The reason why this is very important to see is that many people use a mere pleasure that they derive from meditation as a criterion for their progress. But, pleasure is secondary, and is not something an unawakened being should use to judge things against. Pleasure is not the measure of success, it’s the unshakeable composure of peace in the face of death, that is. Thus, one’s meditation of breath should establish itself upon mindfulness of the impermanence as described above. It should not become something agreeable that one uses for not dealing with the world.

A dying man can only rely upon his wisdom, if he developed it. Wisdom is not dependent upon any phenomenon originated upon six senses. It is developed on the basis of the discernment of the same. That’s why when one’s senses start to wither and die, the knowledge of their nature remains unaffected. When there is no wisdom, there will be despair, in the face of death.

Intentions Behind One’s Actions

[source]

The Right meditation is inseparable from the Right view. That means that even if a person doesn’t have the Right view, their meditation should be concerned about getting it. To put it simply – it comes down to developing the self-transparency (or self-honesty) concerning skilful as skilful (kusala) and unskilful as unskilful (akusala). The Buddha defined the Right view in those very terms – knowing “good as good”, and “bad as bad”. The person with the Right view knows for oneself, beyond any doubt, kusala as kusala and akusala as akusala. By seeing it – he recognizes it. He doesn’t need to hold or adopt any other external criteria. The clarity of his vision pertains to here and now, internally. Thus, for someone who hasn’t achieved that yet, that’s where the meditation should start. Obtaining of the Right criteria and then meditating through it. Keeping it “composed” is the definition of the Right samadhi.

The problem is that this kind of instruction is very non-specific. People today usually need something more proliferated and palpable. They require meditation “methods”. An average man today wants a “recipe”, a prescription of “steps”. He needs to know what exactly he should do, that would then automatically result in his liberation. Unfortunately, it doesn’t work like that. If we look at the Suttas, whenever the Buddha was talking about meditation it was to bring the fulfilment of knowledge and wisdom. Yet, if a person has none of the latter to begin with, then the fulfilment cannot arise nor be fabricated mechanically. Very often the Buddha’s reply on how to meditate would be in instructing people in recognizing and avoiding the unskilful, and cultivating (bhavana) of the skilful. Discerning the nature of kusala and akusala has the potential of taking the mind above both. Freeing it from action (kamma) and it’s results (vipaka), since they are bound to the domain of skilful and unskilful. And that’s exactly why performing (doing or acting) of the specific steps, cannot take one beyond the nature of kamma. Understanding it however, might.

Furthermore, methods and techniques usually don’t amount to more than management of the problem of suffering. Management of something cannot actually uproot that very thing. So, instead of that, a person will be better of in trying to discern what kind of attitude towards meditation can be sustained throughout the day. An attitude that wouldn’t need any particular favorable environment or special conditions to be applied in. Regardless of whether one is sitting in a full lotus posture, or just walking down the street. One needs to find that kind of composure that one can maintain in both circumstances. The way to do this is if the composure is established upon the general mindfulness. Not the particular observation and adherence to the prescribed steps of a “meditation” technique, that results in one being absorbed in it. Absorption is the opposite of general mindfulness.

Every jhana for example is fully founded upon the basis of the unshakeable mindfulness as number of Suttas often mention. So, even if a person wants to do his meditation in a “formal” manner, such as sit for an hour few times a day, that is fine. As long as it is not done for the purpose of developing some sort of “experience of absoption” out of it. Like trying to watch one’s breath hoping for some novelty energy release. The point of meditation is to remain present as much as possible. Present or mindful of whatever is already there (feelings, perceptions, intentions). Not interfere with it, or deny it, or try to replace it. Just discerning the enduring presence of the arisen experience. Emotionally, perceptually and intentionally. That kind of composure can then be “spread out” over one’s entire day, even when a person is not sitting down to meditate.

And this should not be too hard to grasp (though that doesn’t mean it will be easy to accept). The whole point of the practice of Dhamma and meditation is nothing other than understanding of the nature of things. The understanding that arises on account of mindful discerning of whatever is arisen and enduring in our experience. And it’s that understanding of the unskilful that frees the mind from it. If a person wants to be truly free once and for all, the only way to do so is through the knowledge and mindfulness.

Thus, if one wants to practice in a manner that pertains to this final goal of freedom, he needs to become very mindful and honest about intentionality behind any actions. Simple actions, more complex ones, careless or important, big or small – actions of any kind done by body, speech or mind. One will need to attend to them mindfully until the motivation and intentions behind is fully seen. That is because it is the intention that defines wholesome action as wholesome and unwholesome as unwholesome. The “reason” for one’s action so to speak. That’s where skilfulness of an action is rooted at. That’s also the real “reason”, the one deep inside that one might not be willing to admit to oneself. If a person is able to reach the full transparency of one’s intentional actions and its roots, that person is a step closer in discerning what makes kusala as kusala and akusala as akusala. That person is a step closer to the beginning of the Right criteria or view.

So, if one needs to meditate, one needs to be concerned with one’s actions and choices. (Which is also why sila or virtue comes before the Dhamma). In such manner any motivation for one’s intentions behind doing this or that will reveal and not taken at its face value. Through this persistent self-questioning one can also see whether an action that is about to be, is rooted in an unskilful motive. Like sensuality, ill will, vanity or distraction for example. Furthermore, one would need to abandon only that. The unwholesome. One doesn’t need to cancel the entire arisen experience and behaviour. That would be a form of overdoing it, and not using mindfulness as a criteria of discernment. “Is what I am about to do rooted in greed? Lust? How about ill-will and annoyance or anger?” Or “am I acting out of a desire for distraction and forgetfulness? Am I willingly giving in to acts and desires that would delude me further and mask the unskilful basis of those very actions?” Such questioning about the personal and inner dimension of one’s daily experiences and actions will have to result in being mindful. This is a definition of (proper) vipassana or investigation, since that’s exactly what’s being done. Self investigating the motivation behind any actions. And it is obvious to see how this kind of attitude and mindful practice would result in discerning “good as good, bad as bad”. How it would not be dependent on any external authority or belief. Instead be a direct, visible, universal criteria seen personally for oneself.

It’s important to note it is not necessary that one becomes neurotic or obsessed (though it might happen) about it. Always having to actually ask oneself “what am I doing?” before every action. What’s important is the attitude of such questioning. The “answer” is already implied within it. One already knows why one is acting. Whether one is aware of it or not, that’s a different matter. Of course, until that attitude is developed and refined, a person will have to endure possible loss of (superficial) confidence and choice paralysis. That’s because the implications of one’s smallest actions are becoming more revealed. A person starts to feel responsible even for things that are not in his control.

So through this kind of “revealing” of the roots of one’s actions, one is simultaneously becoming less and less able to ignore one’s true intentions. One will not be able to turn a blind eye towards acting good while the real motivation underneath it isn’t necessarily so. That’s why this attitude is “self-transparent”. Whatever is on the surface, one simultaneously sees beneath it as well.

Consequently, one will be able to also see if something is genuinely not rooted in greed, aversion or delusion. In such case even if the whole world comes to tell him that that’s still “bad”, his discernment would remain unshaken. As mentioned above, that’s because good and bad are defined by the intention behind them. Not by the common tradition, views and opinions, duty and culture, but by whether greed, aversion and delusion underlies them.

It should be clear by now that the self-honesty or transparency is not an optional thing (or just one of different ways leading to the same goal). It’s an absolute pre-requisite for any chance of getting the Right view and knowing how to practice the Dhamma. If a person still has difficulties in abandoning own dependence upon a particular “method” of practice, they can still take up this practice of self-questioning all the time, as a “method”. Although not ideal, it will still result in seeing through the motivation and emotional need for any methods in the first place. (Needing “something to do”.) By seeing the subtle motivation under any action, one will automatically feel responsible for one’s choices. No matter how “justified” those might seem externally. The weight on it is always on oneself, and that’s something that one cannot ignore any further.

It is also then when the full weight of the Buddha’s “beings are owners of one’s actions” saying, is truly felt.

The Necessity of Celibacy

[source]

Practice of celibacy is always beneficial. Even for a lay person, who is not necessarily Buddhist or familiar with the Dhamma. The obvious reason for its benefits is the inevitable increase of the mental strength that comes with the restraint. This restraint is intentional and aims at a very powerful desire that otherwise shapes and controls one’s whole life. Sensuality/sexuality is something that heavily contributes towards defining one’s actions and choices. It is something that has at least some influence in virtually all of them.

Thus, adopting a practice of restraint of the sensual desire, a person will be going against that grain of the natural sexual pull of one’s own body. Through willingly imposing this restraint, the mind will be pressured to grow – in terms of strength and in terms of enduring of itself. (As the case with any strength development is. Gradually increasing resistance, increases the capacity to hold the very same.)

Sometimes people think that not having sexual intercourse is all that being celibate means. That doesn’t constitute the celibacy we are talking about here. The difference is to not be celibate only because the current circumstances are presenting no options, but to actually be celibate as a result of determination and practice of restraint. (And then one might decide to live in the circumstance that present no options, and that’s fine.) It’s important to not misunderstand this. We are not saying that one somehow needs to be tempting oneself with sensuality. “Flirting” with it, so to speak, to keep reinforcing the practice of saying “no” to it. That’s ridiculous. And completely misguided and countering the right efforts. Flirting with sensuality can only be done out of sensuality. (As the Buddha said, it’s not possible to have sensual perception without the mind being bound by sensuality.) So, tempting oneself with sensuality, it’s already a form of engaging with sensuality. As such, it goes against the practice of the celibate determinations.

“Firstly, a man who claims to be perfectly celibate does not mutually engage in sex with a woman. However, they consent to being anointed, massaged, bathed, and rubbed by a woman. They enjoy it and like it and find it satisfying. This is a corruption, flaw, blemish, or taint in celibacy. This is called one who lives the celibate life impurely, tied to the fetter of sex. They’re not freed from rebirth, old age, death, sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. They’re not freed from suffering, I say.

Furthermore, a man who claims to be perfectly celibate does not mutually engage in sex with a woman. Nor do they consent to massage and bathing. However, they laugh and play and have fun with women.

they gaze into a woman’s eyes;

they listen through a wall or rampart to the sound of women laughing or chatting or singing or crying.

they recall when they used to laugh, chat, and have fun with women;

they see a householder or their child amusing themselves, supplied and provided with the five kinds of sensual pleasures;

They don’t see a householder or their child amusing themselves, supplied and provided with the five kinds of sensual pleasures. However, they live the celibate life wishing to be reborn in one of the orders of gods. They think: ‘By this precept or observance or mortification or spiritual life, may I become one of the gods!’ They enjoy it and like it and find it satisfying. This is a corruption, flaw, blemish, or taint in celibacy. This is called one who lives the celibate life impurely, tied to the fetter of sex. They’re not free from rebirth, old age, death, sorrow, lamentation, pain, sadness, and distress. They’re not free from suffering, I say.

As long as I saw that these seven sexual fetters—or even one of them—had not been given up in me, I didn’t announce my supreme perfect awakening in this world with its gods, Maras and Brahmas, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans.

But when I saw that these seven sexual fetters—every one of them—had been given up in me, I announced my supreme perfect awakening in this world with its gods, Maras and Brahmas, this population with its ascetics and brahmins, its gods and humans. Knowledge and vision arose in me: ‘My freedom is unshakable; this is my last rebirth; now there are no more future lives.’”

– Anguttara Nikaya, 7.50

So, it’s this determination, the decision to not engage with sensuality ever again that makes all the difference. Just like when a person is trying to give up smoking for example. It will be much harder to do so if you bring yourself up to decide to never smoke again, as opposed to deciding it to quit it half-heartedly for a month or so. The former would exert much more pressure on an individual and even someone who was not a heavy, but a casual, smoker would feel the whole weight of it. And this is even more true of celibacy. And it is necessary to determine it in such a decisive manner.

Only then the mind will be pushed towards development (provided it doesn’t break) of strength on that corresponding level. Anything short of it, the mind will just tread water until the pressure of sexuality builds up, and then inevitably give in. Determining it decisively, however, means that person’s entire life will have to be affected by the profound shift in significance of ordinary things in day to day life. This is pretty much the main reason why most of the people would be afraid of doing it.

As hard as it might seem, it is still very much possible to succeed with a persistent effort over a period of time. If one modifies one’s environment to support the restraint and to not add more to the already existing pressure, the mind can eventually become dry of the inherent “wetness” of the desires. Then everything in person’s life that was depending on the acts of sensuality and non-restraint, will also “dry out”. A person would be free from it. This refers to the inherent worries of protecting what one has acquired, pains of craving towards what one doesn’t have yet, obstacles of one’s worldly ambitions, and similar. All these things will have no significance any more. They will not be able to cause one to suffer on account of them.

It is also important to mention that the sooner one starts this practice the better. It is not uncommon for people to think that they have time to get older and pursue sexual and sensual desires. And that then afterwards, they can practice restraint and free themselves from desires. Unfortunately, it’s quite the opposite: the longer one waits the harder it will be to discern sensuality and do something about it. With old age, sexuality goes “underground” so to speak. The time comes when the body loses its vigour and the sexuality won’t manifest any more in a form of obvious physical behaviour and thirst. This can mislead a person to believe that they are free from it. What actually happened was that sexuality has now descended from something that was discernible (bodily actions and thoughts of such) to something that’s virtually invisible. A subtle background that becomes a ubiquitous motivation for all sorts of habits, acts and even psychological needs. They wouldn’t carry the sensual flavour to them anymore. A flavour that used to be very clear on the surface of them at all. If the mind hasn’t made the effort, while the aim of the effort was obvious, it won’t be able to do it now. Of course, it is still possible in theory at least. But, when the strength and determination fade with the body, having been left undeveloped for so long, it is very unlikely that that will change. (The Suttas, though, do list few exceptions of very old people reaching arahantship. But those were rare, which is why they were so clearly remembered.)

Thus, the sooner the better. That’s also why many people in time of the Buddha were inspired to see young monks and nuns in prime of their life. Meaning: they were at the time of their lives when sensuality was still available and easy to get. They have not just given it up, but ended up enjoying the practise of restraint and understanding the Dhamma.

“Then that devata said to the Venerable Samiddhi: “You have gone forth while young, bhikkhu, a lad with black hair, endowed with the blessing of youth and strength, in the prime of life, without having dallied with sensual pleasures. Enjoy human sensual pleasures, bhikkhu; do not abandon what is directly visible in order to pursue what takes time.”

“I have not abandoned what is directly visible, friend, in order to pursue what takes time. I have abandoned what takes time in order to pursue what is directly visible. For the Blessed One, friend, has stated that sensual pleasures are time-consuming, full of suffering, full of despair, and the danger in them is still greater, while this Dhamma is directly visible, immediate, inviting one to come and see, applicable, to be personally experienced by the wise.”

— SN 1.20

We must stress here that practice of sense restraint would be beneficial even to those who have no interest in practising the Dhamma – fully or partially. Because if the mind manages to become stronger than the sensual pull, and learns how to go beyond sensual cravings, it will to a great degree go beyond the burdens that come with the sensuality. Burdens that are otherwise unavoidable and bring much worry and suffering. Going beyond sensuality will also lessen the grip of one’s own Ego and all the conceit underlying it would be reduced. The anxieties, lack of satisfaction, guilt over things done in the past – all of that would disappear or be significantly removed. Of course, we can only imagine what greater freedom can be gained, if on top of the steadfast restraint, one also practices the Dhamma instructions towards uprooting even the subtle conceit and cravings.

The entire life of a person most often revolves around following desires. Trying to get what one wants is the most fundamental habit of a human mind. This is quite normal, but the problem is in that what people want is almost always rooted in sensuality. One’s desires are most often aimed at the pursuit of the pleasures gained through physical senses. Pleasant sights, sounds, tastes, smells and touches. Subtle or coarse. If a man begins to learn how to go against this sensual “grain” that exhorts pressure on him, that will already mean a beginning of strength. Of course, mere resistance to such sensual cravings will not be able to uproot the sensuality in itself. For that, understanding of the nature of that sensuality will be necessary. But this is only possible on the basis of the sense restraint. For example, if a person has been adhering to the practice of restraint and abstaining from intentionally giving in to sense desires, that person will be able to see the gratuitous nature of the sensual desire in a form of one’s own thoughts. It is something that has arisen completely uninvited, yet pressures one to act upon it as if it is truly owned by him. Sticking to this kind of reflection can reveal that even things that one does want and desire, are rooted and arisen as something that is fundamentally outside of one’s control. One’s responsibility lies not in preventing those thoughts from arising, but in choosing to delight and entertain them. Or not, as the Buddha would tell. In brief: being able to see the uncontrollable (gratuitous) nature of one’s own desires, one can overcome the pressure that they exhort on him.

The main reason why most people wouldn’t even consider the practice of celibacy is because it’s simply too difficult. Because of that it is also unlikely that a man would choose to do it, outside of some sort of philosophical belief or a religious practice. There just wouldn’t be enough motivation.

To reiterate: freedom from sensuality starts by giving it up first. Saying “no” to it. That is not optional. This initial effort can then enable a person to allow the nature of desire to manifest and arise. As opposed to someone who tries to prevent this, or rather cover it up. This cover up is due to instantaneous giving in to the pressure of desire (if not physically, at least mentally). Or it is due to trying to prevent it and deny it. (The former and the latter correspond to sensual indulgence and self-mortification respectively.)

Giving in to the pressure, distracts one from seeing what is it that pressures him in the first place. Denying it, does the same. If one learns how to endure it through restraint, then it can become clear that there is no pressure of sensuality without one’s body. A person at a face value regards one’s own body as basis for pleasure. It’s seen to be something “free” and “effortless”. Something that belongs to “me”. That in itself is a sufficient reason for giving in to it. Hence, it’s not incidental that the Buddha often compared sensuality to a “bait”.

If one contemplates the necessity of the living healthy body for any sensual engagements (fleeting or otherwise), it can be discerned that even the pleasures that one can gain from it belong to the actual sense organs. As in: pleasures are inseparable and inconceivable without them. Thus, if one wants to overcome the entire domain of sensuality, one can do so by overcoming the ownership of the sense organs (or the body as a whole). And extinguishing of the ownership, i.e. the necessary condition of sensuality, is done by understanding that it was impossible to own the body in the first place. If that were not so, then one’s desires would already be all satisfied (i.e. there would be no desires to begin with). Alternatively, one can contemplate that if one were the true master and owner of one’s own body, that body would not be a subject to illness, aging and death. It would not be liable to accidents, elements, circumstances, etc. This kind of understanding can only be properly developed on the basis of restraint and celibacy. And once it is developed, then the restraint will become a normal mode of behaviour. It will not be a way of “resistance” to the sensual pull any more, because there will be no more senses that can pull one. Senses and their respective desires are a problem only when they are “mine”.

Peripheral Awareness

[source]

Mindfulness done correctly is when the mind is anchored in something. That something must be a thing that is not directly attended to, but instead, has to be a reference point to the attended thing (hence we call it “anchor”). If a thing is not directly attended to but there, we call that thing to be a “background”. It’s a background to a thing we attend (which makes that thing a “foreground”). This is the basic principle of mindfulness, on which we can expand here below.

One begins developing this practice of awareness by being mindful of the experience as a whole. For example, one is mindful of ‘being-seated-on-a-chair-reading-a-Dhamma-essay’. That is one’s situation at that very time. That is one’s experience as a “whole”. This is always the necessary starting point. What is very important is to prevent the tendency to become absorbed in one particular thing. (Feeling, sensations or perception, and similar). Instead, one has to broaden the mindfulness and become aware of the generality of one’s current situation, without losing the sight of the particular either.[1]

Of course, the attempts of discerning the background of one’s current experience will not be perfect in the beginning. One will more often than not fall into a mistake of over-attending one’s experience as a whole. This is a mistake of making that background into an object of one’s attention, defining it, clarifying it, trying to keep it in front. These are all ways of making it a foreground, which means that then something else will be in place of the background.

The natural tendency is to ask “What is then the background?”. This is however a wrong question. And it’s wrong because we are not concerned with the content of the background (or foreground for that matter), which would be the answer to “what?”. Instead our concern should be with nature of it. So one needs to restrain the tendency to clarify what is that “background”, and learn how to start discerning the domain of it. The domain of the “periphery”, its nature, in regard to what is presently enduring here.

Thus, something one attends to directly is what a foreground is at the time. It can be anything that is the current object of one’s attention. That thing has manifested, and it is enduring as such. That’s the basic structural property of one’s experience, there is no problem with this. However, if one wants to develop mindfulness, a step further is necessary. That step is developing the peripheral “vision” in regard to that very same foreground object, but without making that peripheral vision the new object by directly attending to it. The Buddha referred to this as “yoniso manasikara”, which is often translated as “proper attention”. Yoniso manasikara is the correct way of attending to the peripheral. Manasikara means “attention”. Yoni means “womb”. So when a thing is present in the front, in the foreground, its peripheral background is that very “womb” the thing has “came from”, so to speak. Yoniso manasikara is womb-attention, or less literally: a peripheral attention.[2]

Thus, the point is to learn how to attend. Not so much “what”. It’s about discerning the habit of “over-attending” and learning how to not resort to it. This habit manifests through either indulging or resisting the object of one’s attention. Either way, one is fully concerned with it. This is why one must stop trying to “observe” one’s experience as an object of one’s attention and instead, acknowledge it and let it endure on its own. (Let it persist or change-while-remaining-the-same-thing). Once the arisen experience of one’s attention is allowed to be, then gradually and indirectly, discerning of the peripheral domain can manifest.

The most practical way of practising this is through mindfulness of body postures. That’s why these things are often called “foundations” of mindfulness, or “anchors” or “reference points”. It’s because they are always rooted in the background. (E.g. foundations are under; an anchor is at the bottom; the reference point is at the distance. Under, bottom, away… it means ‘not-here-directly-in-front-of-me’). So for example: while I’m seated, I’m reading an article, actively scrolling through the pages, paying attention to what’s being said in it. Things I’m “doing”, like reading, writing, talking, etc. are things I’m attending to (foreground). And I’m attending to them all while I’m seated. That’s the reference point that is enough for proper mindfulness. That is what’s the background here. Yet, if I switch my attention and start attending to the fact that I’m sitting on the chair, then the body posture of “sitting” ceases to be the background in my experience. Why? Because I’ve broken the relationship of “referencing”. There is no more “while”, since I forgot about the reading, and became concerned with sitting. When this happens, one can either go back to the original foreground, or discern the newly present background in regard to the attended experience of sitting. The new background will have to be something even more general than “sitting posture”. And the more general thing in that case is nothing other than awareness of the “body there”.[3]

Body postures are more general than attending to a particular action or perception. But having a “body there” is even more general than the postures. Because to be walking, sitting, standing or lying down, one needs to have a body in the first place. That’s why one can also use the knowledge of “there is body”, as the peripheral anchor for one’s daily actions and experiences. The presence of one’s living body is a fundamental requirement for any action. We can go even higher (even more general), as we mentioned earlier, and develop awareness of the phenomenon of Earth, Water, Fire or Air. Or even further, in the practice of more refined kasinas, as described in the Suttas. The point is that the principle remains the same.

We need to stress that this is something that requires development. It’s not something that can be just “figured out”, or read once and made sense of. It requires a diligent repetition of “stepping back” when over-attending one’s experience as a whole. And then “stepping in” when ignoring it (under-attending it, forgetting about the background). So, it takes time and effort in order for it to be correctly discerned and recognized.

The problem with common practice of meditation is that people are encouraged to get “absorbed” into the particular “meditation object”. The practice becomes a form of focusing on the foreground at the expense of everything else. And not just that, people end up focusing on the objects twice as hard. This is because their view of meditation is to look and perceive the “momentary” foreground (the whole idea of “observing ‘sensations‘”). Then within that they try to perceive even more particular things. So it’s not just the domain of the foreground, but the content proliferates further too. In cases like this, the ‘background’, as a foundation of mindfulness that needs to be understood, is even further obscured.

The ‘reference point’ means being aware of something, without having to actively think about it. That’s the basic principle of mindfulness. This should always be the basis for samadhi (according to the Suttas).[4] That is why, if mindfulness and awareness is practised correctly, it will result in knowledge of the nature of things. The very definition of knowledge is knowing something without having to actively think about it. The knowledge reappears when it is attended to. One knows what one knows. This is the important point because this type of mindfulness of the background that’s simultaneous with the presently arisen phenomenon[5], results in the establishment of mind (samadhi) that transcends sensuality and ill will. The whole domain (scope) of unwholesome.[6] And that’s why that samadhi further results in complete knowledge of liberation.

The catch is in persistent effort of repetition of learning how to attend to things peripherally, without having to “directly” look at them. For a mind affected with avijja, the “direct look”, the “ayoniso manasikara” always involves appropriation and the Self-view. And “learning to attend” things peripherally can be done on many different “bases” or “domains” that are structurally present as the background of our attended experience. These domains are the domain of feelings, thoughts, and even one’s intentions (bodily, verbal and mental).

For example, being aware of the general feeling present, without trying to perceive it as “sensation” (i.e. “in” the body), is another way of establishing the proper mindfulness.

Or, something we often talk about, taking up of personal responsibility. If one takes it up, then no matter what the engagement with the particular task is, the background of it (the “womb” of that engagement) is one’s own choice to engage with it in the first place. Taking up responsibility, means becoming aware of the “background” choices one makes throughout one’s life.[7]

Furthermore, taking up responsibility for what one has chosen, a person gets to maintain that mindfulness through the very particular actions one is doing on account of it. And that mindfulness of responsibility is not something they would have to perpetually think about. No, that mindfulness is being felt instead. (That’s why the initial awareness of any form of responsibility is always unpleasant and concerning).

The choice behind one’s actions is a general unity, a context of one’s acts, that is present in each of those acts individually. Present as a peripheral background. It is because of this that sila or virtue is a necessary prerequisite for understanding. When one’s actions are based on distortions of priority (particular sensuality over general nature of choice regarding it, for example), one cannot see a clear responsible background while engaged in such pursuits. No perspective, so to speak. So, first actions that maintain absorptions with particularity must be divorced from the unwholesome domain. Then they must be further restrained, by avoiding the distracting of oneself. By undoing wrong way of attending to things. By not cultivating improper attention. Only then can one begin to discern the signs of the peripheral, characteristics of the background hereby discussed. Only then one will be able to “grasp the sign of one’s mind” or cittanimitta. A necessary requirement for the arising of the Right view.

This is why the correct practice of mindfulness results in higher establishments of mind (samadhi). For example, this is where mind surmounts the fundamental “generality” of form, by the way of surmounting the generality of earth, water, fire and air. Also, there is a reason that the order of elements always stays the same. They are have a particular structural order of their generality. And one can discern them in that order only. [back]

That’s also why this type of attention is said by the Buddha to be one of the necessary pre-requisites for the arising of the Right view. [back]

“…or mindfulness that “there is body” is simply established in him to the extent necessary for the final knowledge.”

– MN 10, Satipatthana Sutta [back]

“Unification of mind, friend Visakha, is samadhi. The four foundations of mindfulness are the basis of samadhi. The four right kind of striving are the equipment of samadhi. The repetition, the development and cultivation of those same states is what development of samadhi is.”

– MN 44, Culavedalla Sutta [back]

Experience as a whole, the ‘foreground-without-focusing-on-particular-object-witin-it’. [back]

Sensuality is always concerned with the particular content of the experience. Particular sight, sound, smell, taste, touch. Thus, mindfulness of the peripheral domain to the particular foreground, can result in overcoming it. [back]

Hence the fully developed knowledge that came from the Right View, results in freeing an individual from his actions (kamma). Full understanding of the nature of the “choice” as “peripheral”, removes the gratuitous assumption (upadana) of necessity of the “Chooser” i.e. the Self. Understanding the choice or intentional intention (cetana) frees oneself from choosing (i.e. acting). [back]

Warning: No link definition for link ID 'while' found on line 543 Warning: No link definition for link ID 'to be' found on line 884 Warning: No link definition for link ID 'as that by which' found on line 899

257hh- Only The Noble Truth Of Pain

[source]

]

Q: The four noble truths, you're saying, are four aspects to one insight.

Nm: The insight being the way out of suffering. You see how to escape from it without trying to get rid of it. If you want to understand the way out of suffering, first you need to understand the suffering, and you can't understand the suffering if you can't give up the pressure, the need, the urge, the craving to get rid of it, to manage it, to prevent it. You need to endure and not act out of the pressure towards more pleasure when you're feeling agreeable. You need to endure and not act out of the pressure towards getting rid of the pain when you're feeling disagreeable. You need to endure and not act out of the pressure to ignore the neither-pleasant-nor-unpleasant feeling. That type of endurance is the hardest thing to do.

“Patient endurance is the supreme austerity. Khantī paramaṁ tapo titikkhā..”

– Dhp 179-196

That's why people find sense-restraint difficult because you have to endure that pressure of craving. That's why they find it difficult to NOT try and manage their suffering, but instead explain it or psychologize it, because that endurance is very difficult. That's why people find it really hard to not distract themselves when they're feeling neither-pleasant-nor-unpleasant, to not find something to do, to not find an activity to keep them occupied, because it just becomes too unpleasant.

If you endure things on the level of not acting out of craving towards whatever is felt or out of unwholesome intentions, you are practising the highest of all ascetic practices, and the only one that matters. That is the endurance that results in the uprooting of craving and the cessation of dukkha.

If you endure things on that right level, you will not need much of an instruction because you already have the right basis, which can lead to the obvious aspects of your situation being revealed, such as, “Okay, so I am liable to suffering and everything I've been doing so far, has not uprooted it, has not even been in the direction of uprooting that suffering, it was all only on the level of management and distraction from it, and the Dhamma is the direction of uprooting, so it's completely the opposite direction in which I have been going so far.” But for that insight to arise, you first need to endure things on the right level.

You have to understand the suffering first, in order to see the way out. In order for you to understand suffering, you need to stop trying to get rid of it and trying to manage the suffering. You need to allow it to be, to endure, because it takes time to understand it. By covering up the suffering, by trying to get rid of it, by trying to manage it, you are not uprooting it, if you were, it would not return.

Can you endure the pain without expressing it, without trying to repress it or trying to get rid of it, without psychologizing it, without hateful thoughts, without turning away and ignoring it? Can you just stay with it?

Q: Can I endure my liability to suffer without doing anything on account of it? I could say, “Ok, I am now going to endure the suffering so that I can get rid of it!”

Nm: So, you started enduring the suffering, maybe for one second, in the right way? And then the next second, you fall into, “Now I'm enduring it because I want to get rid of it”. So what do you do then? Well, you include that into your endurance of suffering that you don't want to get rid of.

You can endure the suffering, rightly, but then you can endure it wrongly if you become motivated by different reasons, such as, you're not enduring it for its own sake, you're doing it to get rid of it, which means that you have just returned to the old attitude. So how do you stop that? By enduring it, it's not going to be perfect but for as long as you know that you are supposed to endure it without acting out of it, then even that mind that makes that ‘endurance’ as an act of craving, will calm down if you endure it sufficiently enough without turning away.

Q:\

“...This is the dukkha ariya·sacca/noble truth of suffering:\ 1- jāti/birth is dukkha,\ 2-jarā/decaying is dukkha,\ 3-maraṇa/death is dukkha,\ 4-association with the disliked is dukkha,\ 5-separation from the liked is dukkha,\ 6-not getting what one wants is dukkha;\ 7-in short, the pañcupādānakkhandhā/ five assumed aggregates are dukkha…”

Nm: Basically, your life is the basis for your dukkha. That's it. It's not like particular things are the basis for your dukkha, the ‘five aggregates’ are the basis for the dukkha. In other words, you haven't done anything wrong, you were just born. Birth is dukkha, that's it. Even if you don't do anything particularly wrong, you're already affected with dukkha because you're already here. Everything else that comes throughout your life is kind of a secondary reminder of what the dukkha already is and that you are already liable to it. That's why a person needs to develop the state of mind that recognises this and restrains themselves from trying to address those myriad of individual instances of suffering, “Oh, he said, that upset me, she didn't do that which upset me, I'll go talk to her, I'll tell him off,….all so that I can address the suffering”.

“He abused me, he attacked me, he defeated me, he robbed me.” Those who harbour such thoughts will never end their hatred.\ “He abused me, he attacked me, he defeated me, he robbed me.” Those who do not harbour such thoughts will end their hatred.\ Hatred never ends through hatred; by non-hatred alone does it end. This is an eternal truth."

– Dhp 1 Yamaka Vagga

All of these things that you experienced throughout the life that involved suffering are not the reason for your suffering, if they were, freedom from suffering would not be possible. It's your craving in regard to how you feel on account of these things in the world, that's the root of suffering. For as long as you keep acting out towards him or her or this or that, or particular instances of suffering, you're not allowing yourself to see it on the right level, which means you cannot address it correctly. You're still blaming the individual circumstances.

A view needs to be developed, whereby you recognise that it's not about instances of suffering, it's about the fact that you are liable to suffer. That's it. If it's not this instance that you suffer in regard to, it would have been something else and it will be something else. You, trying to manage and perfect your ways of managing your environment, the way you speak to people, the way they speak to you, all of that is basically rooted in the fact that you know deep down, that you don't know the escape from suffering, and you just want to minimise the pain, you want to manage it. And for as long as you value that management, you will not force yourself to look for the direction of uprooting suffering. That's the trap of thinking, “Oh, this management technique is helpful. My psychotherapy is helpful, psychology is helpful, watching my breath is helpful, etc...”. All these management's are helpful to manage your pain, but if you become dependent on management of the symptoms, you are not going to be able to endure the symptoms so to reveal the source of your illness, because you immediately cover up the symptoms, you manage it, you take a pill, you deal with the symptoms, and they're gone and now you don't see the illness and think that ‘you suffering less than you used to’ means that the illness is ending, yet you are still as liable to dukkha as before, that hasn't changed.

You need to endure the symptom by resisting the pressure to manage it and by not managing the discomfort, you get to understand, “Right, now it's this that I'm suffering over, yesterday was something else, tomorrow it will be something else, the point is, I am liable to suffering and even if I perfectly address this and that issue, I cannot prevent circumstances from making me uncomfortable in the future and that's the problem.” You can realise that it's not about particular sufferings, it's about the nature of suffering.

Q: I am infected by craving and affected by feeling. I am thus liable to suffering.

Nm: These particular instances of affections are just the reminders of your situation that's already within that liability. Birth, as in manifestation, is already suffering, you are manifested from the moment you're born. For as long as your manifestation is here, dukkha is here. That's it. Even if you don't experience anything uncomfortable, no incidents, you are still within dukkha, you are still liable. That's why a person doesn't need great misfortunes and so on to recognise the nature of their situation, “I am liable to suffer”.

Q: I'm affected by things. Things happen. I feel them.

Nm: You feel them either pleasant, unpleasant or neutral. Which means at any given time, there is some pressure placed on you. Even though you might say, “Oh, see now it's all fine. I'm not affected by suffering.” , but just ask yourself, “Am I feeling something? Yes”, Well, to that extent, suffering is implicit, you are pressured to that extent. You are liable to feelings. Can you even conceive being in control of your feelings? Saying I should feel this and I should not feel that? No, that's only on the level of wishful thinking. Liability to feelings means liability to suffering. You have no say in what feeling arises and how long it persists. You know that they change. For example, you might have a pleasant feeling, you had it so many times before, but you also know that it has to cease at some point, which means, if you're honest with yourself, that through a mere change of feeling, whatever feeling is there, you will have to experience suffering to some extent.

Are you able then to not be pressured by anything that you feel at any given time? Even pleasure pressures you. It makes you nervous, “What if I lose this? What if it doesn't last long enough? I want more of it? How to protect it? How do I get it again?” That's not actually a peaceful state. Pain, obviously it's not a peaceful state either, and in terms of neutral feeling, one thinks that it's boring, which is very much not peaceful, although it's peaceful, there's nothing happening. Yet, nothing happening is the most frightening thing for the ignorant mind.

Q: There are just three types of feeling, just three types of pain.

Nm: Well, three types of feeling means one type of pain, one dukkha. As it says in the Suttas, “Whatever is felt counts as suffering in the discipline of the noble one.” If you have the right view, if you understand the nature of feelings, you understand that whatever is felt is unpleasant because it's felt.

”..Good, good, bhikkhu! These three feelings have been spoken of by me: pleasant feeling, painful feeling, neither-painful-nor-pleasant feeling. These three feelings have been spoken of by me. And I have also said: ‘Whatever is felt is included in suffering.’ That has been stated by me with reference to the impermanence of sankharas. That has been stated by me with reference to sankharas being subject to destruction … to sankharas being subject to vanishing … to sankharas being subject to fading away … to sankharas being subject to cessation … to sankharas being subject to change…”

– SN 36.11

Q: If you feel, that means you are affected, and therefore you can know that you are infected, you have a disease.

Nm: Exactly. Feeling is a symptom of an underlying problem. You're subjected to and imprisoned by, trapped within a disease. But if you don't see that as a symptom, as I said, if you still feel justified and have the view that management of suffering, management of symptoms, doing something about it so to overcome it when it arises, if you don't abandon that view, and if you don't restrain yourself, you're not going to see how deep the illness goes. Which means you're not going to see the source of it.

Q: If I am aware of feeling, I am aware of dukkha.

Nm: If you're aware of feeling correctly. What is the feeling? Most people would, through those views of management, proliferation and confusing information for understanding, would think that feelings are physical sensations that they have in their body. No, feeling is a state of mind, feeling is always mental. Feelings in regard to the body are always mental. And there's only three types of feeling on that level, which is the level of feeling agreeable, disagreeable, and neither-agreeable-or-disagreeable.

"...It’s for one who feels that I declare: ‘This is suffering’ … ‘This is the origin of suffering’ … ‘This is the cessation of suffering’ … ‘This is the practice that leads to the cessation of suffering...’.

– AN 3.61

Q:

“This is the dukkha·samudaya ariya·sacca/the noble truth of the origin of suffering:\ 1-Taṇhā/urge/inclination/craving,\ 2-which perpetuates being,\ 3-connected with craving and passion,\ 4-finding delight here or there,\ 5-that is to say: kāma-taṇhā/sensual desire, bhava-taṇhā/desire for being and vibhava-taṇhā/desire for non-being.”

Nm: That brings us to the point I've already said, the origin, the source, the basis, the necessary condition for presence of dukkha is presence of craving. It's not what you've seen, smelt, tasted, touched, thought about, remembered, etc. It's about craving towards whatever is felt there and then, that's the root of dukkha. The world or samsara is not the dukkha. It's not the cause of suffering. It's your attitude, on that emotional level, towards samsara, that's what suffering is. It's your craving towards it. What craving? Craving for more pleasure in pleasant feeling, craving for less pain in a painful feeling, craving for ignorance and distraction in a neutral feeling. That's it, that's the root of the entire universe of suffering. But in order to get to the root, you need to stop acting out of that craving, which is trying to manage your suffering.

The gradual training, the prerequisites in the form of a lifestyle that the Buddha outlined, is the way of rounding up, towards the centre of that suffering, which is your craving, which is an internal thing. However, if your lifestyle still revolves around the pursuit of sense pleasures, management of your suffering, trying to get rid of pain, acting out of pain through unwholesome acts of anger, distracting activities, avoidance of boredom and solitude, etc. There's no way you're going to uproot craving, when you're still physically, still passionately engaged in maintaining it. First, you need to physically stop acting out of it, then verbally, then mentally, then you can eventually see the roots, see your own attitude towards what's currently felt.

You want to act out of craving because you feel confined within it. You can escape from that confinement by giving up sensuality, when it's pleasant, by giving up management of pain when it's unpleasant, and by giving up distraction and indolence when it's neutral. That will reveal your confining situation and the fundamental resistance you have towards the senses that we spoke of before. And if you continue not to act out of craving, the mind will calm down within that and then you get to see the escape.

“Near Sāvatthī. As he was standing to one side, Pañcālacaṇḍa the deva’s son recited this verse in the Blessed One’s presence:”Truly in a confining place, he found an opening—the one of extensive wisdom, the awakened one who awakened to jhāna, the chief bull, withdrawn, the sage."

The Buddha:”Even in a confining place they find it, the Dhamma for the attainment of Nibbana. Those who have gained recollection, are rightly composed.”

– SN 2.7

That's wisdom, it's not a magical result of some method or some accidental insight. When you get to see dukkha for what it is through your act of non-craving, then that craving, that dukkha will begin to evaporate because it requires you to ignore it for its maintenance. You remove it indirectly by not providing a basis for craving to grow and then it will dry up.

Q:

This is the dukkha·nirodha ariya·sacca/the noble truth of the cessation of suffering:\ 1-the complete virāga/dispassion,\ 2-nirodha/cessation,\ 3-cāgo/abandoning,\ 4-paṭinissaggo/giving up,\ 5-mutti/release and\ 6-anālayo/detachment from that very taṇhā.

Nm: Cessation of craving means cessation of the possibility to suffer on account of anything, that the senses, the aggregates, the world brings you, good or bad, doesn't matter. You cannot suffer because you cannot crave.

Q:

This is the dukkha·nirodha·gāminī paṭipada ariya·sacca/ the noble truth of the path leading to the cessation of suffering: just this ariya aṭṭhaṅgika magga/ noble eightfold path, that is to say:\ 1-sammā·diṭṭhi/right view,\ 2-sammā·saṅkappa/right resolve,\ 3-sammā·vācā/right speech,\ 4-sammā·kammanta/right action,\ 5-sammā·ājīva/right livelihood,\ 6-sammā·vāyāma/right effort,\ 7-sammā·sati/ right recollection,\ 8-sammā·samādhi/ right composure.

Nm: The right view comes first. You need to know, “The root of the craving is not in the world. It's not due to insufficient management or not having a perfect meditation technique or something else. It's in the craving towards what I'm feeling, nothing else.” Therefore, you first need to stop acting out of craving, and then your resolves, your speech, actions, livelihood and efforts need to start matching that principle. That's the noble eightfold path.

Then in the pleasure, there will just be the pleasure, there will be no more implicit craving for wanting more of it. There's nothing more there's nothing less because you're not resisting it, nor leaning towards it. It's not touching you, it's not yours anymore, which means it's not pressuring you. There's nothing wanted in regard to it and nothing not wanted in regard to it either. Not touching or being touched by it, it is no longer felt.

"...Ven. Udayin said to Ven. Sariputta, "But what is the pleasure here, my friend, where there is nothing felt?"

"Just that is the pleasure here, my friend: where there is nothing felt…"

– AN 9.34

258hh- Simile of The Son’s Flesh

[source]

SN 12.63 Puttamansa Sutta: A Son's Flesh:

“At Savatthi…“There are these four nutriments for the maintenance of beings who have come into being or for the support of those in search of a place to be born. Which four? Physical food, gross or refined; contact as the second, mental intention the third, and consciousness the fourth. These are the four nutriments for the maintenance of beings who have come into being or for the support of those in search of a place to be born.

“And how is physical food to be regarded? Suppose a couple, husband & wife, taking a few provisions, were to travel through a desert. With them would be their only dear baby son. Then the few provisions of the couple going through the desert would be used up while there was still a stretch of the desert yet to be crossed. The thought would occur to them, ‘Our few provisions are used up while there is still a stretch of this desert yet to be crossed. What if we were to kill our only dear baby son, and make dried meat. That way, chewing on the flesh of our son, at least the two of us would make it through this desert. Otherwise, all three of us would perish.’ So they would kill their only dear baby son, and make dried meat. Chewing on the flesh of their son, they would make it through the desert. While eating the flesh of their only son, they would beat their breasts, crying, ‘Where have you gone, our only dear baby son? Where have you gone, our only dear baby son?’ Now what do you think, monks: Would that couple eat that food playfully or for intoxication, or for putting on bulk, or for beautification?”

“No, lord.”

“Wouldn’t they eat that food simply for the sake of making it through that desert?”

“Yes, lord.”

"In the same way, I tell you, is the nutriment of physical food to be regarded. When physical food is understood, passion for the five cords of sensual pleasures is understood. When passion for the five cords of sensual pleasure is understood, there is no fetter bound by which a disciple of the noble ones would come back again to this world.

"And how is the nutriment of contact to be regarded? Suppose a flayed cow were to stand leaning against a wall. The creatures living in the wall would chew on it. If it were to stand leaning against a tree, the creatures living in the tree would chew on it. If it were to stand exposed to water, the creatures living in the water would chew on it. If it were to stand exposed to the air, the creatures living in the air would chew on it. For wherever the flayed cow were to stand exposed, the creatures living there would chew on it. In the same way, I tell you, is the nutriment of contact to be regarded. When the nutriment of contact is understood, the three feelings, pleasure, pain, neither-pleasure-nor-pain are understood. When the three feelings are understood, I tell you, there is nothing further for a disciple of the noble ones to do.

"And how is the nutriment of mental intention to be regarded? Suppose there were a pit of glowing embers, deeper than a man’s height, full of embers that were neither flaming nor smoking, and a man were to come along, loving life, hating death, loving pleasure, resisting pain, and two strong men, having grabbed him by the arms, were to drag him to the pit of embers. To get far away would be that man’s intention, far away would be his wish, far away would be his aspiration. Why is that? Because he would realize, ‘If I fall into this pit of glowing embers, I will meet with death from that cause, or with death-like pain.’ In the same way, I tell you, is the nutriment of mental intention to be regarded. When the nutriment of mental intention is understood, the three forms of craving for sensual pleasures, craving for being, and craving for non-being are understood. When the three forms of craving are understood, I tell you, there is nothing further for a disciple of the noble ones to do.

“And how is the nutriment of consciousness to be regarded? Suppose that, having arrested a thief, a criminal, they were to show him to the king: ‘This is a thief, a criminal for you, your majesty. Impose on him whatever punishment you like.’ So the king would say, ‘Go, men, and shoot him in the morning with a hundred spears.’ So they would shoot him in the morning with a hundred spears. Then the king would say at noon, ‘Men, how is that man?’ ‘Still alive, your majesty.’ So the king would say, ‘Go, men, and shoot him at noon with a hundred spears.’ So they would shoot him at noon with a hundred spears. Then the king would say in the evening, ‘Men, how is that man?’ ‘Still alive, your majesty.’ So the king would say, ‘Go, men, and shoot him in the evening with a hundred spears.’ So they would shoot him in the evening with a hundred spears. Now what do you think, monks: Would that man, being shot with three hundred spears a day, experience pain and distress from that cause?”

“Even if he were to be shot with only one spear, lord, he would experience pain and distress from that cause, to say nothing of three hundred spears.”

“In the same way, I tell you, monks, is the nutriment of consciousness to be regarded. When the nutriment of consciousness is understood, name&form are understood. When name&form are understood, I tell you, there is nothing further for a disciple of the noble ones to do.”

Q: How to develop complete dispassion towards food?

Nm: By developing that context that the “son’s flesh simile” outlined. That will prevent you from having any passion towards food. The simile is not just some shocking poetry. No, imagine eating your own child, how would that feel while you are trying to survive? Now take that context and apply to any food you eat. That’s how it should feel, that’s the context that you need to sustain. Why? Because the mind will completely turn away from any enjoyment, amusement and any lust towards edible food, edible nutriment, which in return will completely remove any attachment and desire towards the five cords of sensual pleasure because that’s what it all comes down to, your consumption of pleasure.

You wouldn’t be lost in your consumption of food, you would eat only to the point of overcoming hunger for survival. You wouldn’t eat for the sake of eating, for the sake of chewing, for the sake of enjoying, you would only have one goal in your mind. So whenever you eat, always bring that context up, even before you start eating, bring that context up, and then you’ll see whether you need to eat and how much to eat, and if there is any passion towards what you’re eating. There won’t be passion there if you sustain this context because it cannot survive in that environment.

Who knows, maybe their child tasted very nice, in terms of the actual taste, but it doesn’t mean that at any given time, mother and father who loved their child, could have enjoyed it. So it’s not that the mouth won’t perceive agreeability of texture and taste, but in any case, that’s not the basis for passion. Loss of context is the basis for passion for agreeability of taste.

Q: Should I be concerned about how I’m eating?

Nm: No, I wouldn’t worry about the way you’re eating. If the context is there, it doesn’t matter which way you’re eating.

Q: Would it be useful to try to think about the process of the consumption, like, thinking the food is going inside the body and not going inside ‘Me’, or it’s for the body which isn’t “mine”, and it’s not for my enjoyment and so on?

Nm: All of that is kind of psychologizing. All of those “insights” and the way you can describe it are fine, if the context is there. The context of eating for the right reason only, not too much, not too little, not overthinking it, certainly not giving in to the enjoyment, craving and emotional dependence on agreeable food. But if that context is not there, then, you can analyse it, visualise it in certain ways, and you can contemplate how it’s just going into the body which is not yours, etc, but fundamentally, the passion is still there. So that’s why the Buddha gave such a drastic simile. All those kinds of thoughts that you try to use when eating, although true, won’t work, because the lust is rooted deeper than that. What will work is when you don’t want to eat it, but you have to and what will work even more when you don’t want to eat it, but you have to and what you have to eat is what is dearest to you. It’s not meant to be eaten, so then there will not be even a grain of your being that would want to be eating it, you will only eat to survive. Purely. Same with the simile of the charcoal pit and burning embers, if two men come and drag you towards that pit, your mind would want to be anywhere else except there. Intention would go in any direction except to the pit.

Q: Why can’t I just enjoy my food? Why can’t I just eat it?

Nm: Because it doesn’t belong to you. Your body doesn’t belong to you. So how can you eat the food as if it’s yours? You can enjoy it if you want. It’s not like you cannot. Yes, you can. But then you have to suffer the consequences. In the same sense a fish suffers consequences when he eats the food that a fisherman puts on a hook. The fish enjoys it and as a result of that gets hooked. So it’s not that we are outlining some moral law here that you must hate your food and eat it like it’s your only child. Do what you like, eat and enjoy if you want to.

Q: But what’s the danger?

Nm: Well, exactly. You already know that there is some danger, that’s the point. Why do people not like to think about the illness, their own illness or even illness of people that are dear to them? Mortality? Ageing,? Why is that? There must be something there that people don’t want to admit. Well, chasing pleasure of food or otherwise is tied to that. So if you stop and think about it, you would see that maybe, “I could enjoy food, I could enjoy the senses. But what if there is a catch there?” And again, even the most untrained mind can see, even if you don’t know anything about the Dhamma, no values of precepts or whatever else, everybody at some point in their life, sooner or later, thinks, “What’s the point in chasing sensual desires, food or otherwise, when it only results in a very, very temporary satisfaction?”

The point is, you already have an inkling that, “Oh, so there is no end to this. And I’m kind of enslaved by it. And that’s not a good position to be in. But hey, I’ll forget about that because I’ll chase the next desire, and next desire and next desire.” And that’s how people go through life. So yes, you can do that. But again, there are consequences that you will have to pay the price for. Price of eating, consuming and taking all these things up, that don’t belong to you. Then at the end, the bill comes and you realise, “Oh, now I have to pay for all of that. I thought it was mine. I thought I was the owner. I thought it was free.” But it’s not. If it were free, it wouldn’t be pressuring you so much. It wouldn’t be enticing you so much. It wouldn’t be trapping you so much, it wouldn’t be baiting you so much. There’s always a catch.

Q:

“When lust for the five types of sensual pleasure is fully understood there is no fetter bound by which the noble disciple might come back to this world.”

Nm: Fully understanding lust and assumptions in regard to the solid food, you will fully understand and remove the ownership of the physical body that depends on the solid food, it won’t be taken as yours anymore. By fully understanding the body, and as the Buddha said in another sutta, by being fully developed in regard to your own body, you will fully overcome the lust towards the five types of sensual pleasure.

Q:

“And how is the nutriment of phassa/contact/pressure to be regarded? Suppose a flayed cow were to stand leaning against a wall. The creatures living in the wall would chew on it. If it were to stand leaning against a tree, the creatures living in the tree would chew on it. If it were to stand exposed to water, the creatures living in the water would chew on it. If it were to stand exposed to the air, the creatures living in the air would chew on it. For wherever the flayed cow were to stand exposed, the creatures living there would chew on it. In the same way, I tell you, is the nutriment of contact/pressure to be regarded. When the nutriment of contact/pressure is understood, the three feelings ,pleasure, pain, neither-pleasure-nor-pain are understood. When the three feelings are understood, I tell you, there is nothing further for a disciple of the noble ones to do.”

Nm: That’s why I like to translate phassa/contact as pressure. It’s not an impersonal, mechanical or biological “contact”. It’s the mental pressure. Phassa is the pressure to act on account of what is felt, and that’s exactly how the cow is feeling. It’s not just nonchalant about creatures anatomically chewing on its flesh. No, it’s pressured, it’s harassed, it’s annoyed. It’s attacked, it’s being devoured, it’s uncomfortable. “Contact” is uncomfortable. So do you regard phassa as uncomfortable or do you not even see it as a pressure at all? If that’s the case, your understanding of or your idea of phassa is very inaccurate. And usually it’s very inaccurate. People usually think, due to the whole commentarial misrepresentation which explains phassa as a physical coming together of the senses, sense objects and consciousness, and then ‘poof!’, the result of that is sight, sound,etc. As if it has nothing to do with me, and I’m not responsible for it. No, phassa is indeed having eyes and sights, but it’s being pressured on account of what is felt in regard to that. That’s where phassa is.

So in other words, if people want to understand phassa, if they want to understand the situation of that cow, then find things within your mind, where you are emotionally pressured, on account of anything, sight, sound, smell, taste, touch, thought, doesn’t matter. If there is pressure there, if there is discomfort there, that’s where phassa is. And that’s what needs to be understood, not psychologically or anatomically explained in terms of sense organs and so on. That’s not the phassa.

Imagine the cow being devoured by the insects, and you’re telling it, “Oh, no, see, this is what’s happening to you. In dependence on the body and bodily-touches, body-consciousness arises. The meeting of the three is contact. With contact as condition, feeling.”, “Okay, yeah, but I’m still pressured, I still suffer. So that knowledge of the explanation of the contact is not freeing me from this discomfort. Thus, it’s not the knowledge because if that knowledge truly pertains to the nature of that phenomenon, it will result in freedom from suffering, as the suttas would say.” The full understanding of contact results in you being free from the pressure.

“Seeing thus, the instructed noble disciple experiences revulsion towards the body, towards bodily phenomena, towards body-consciousness, towards body-contact, towards feeling. Experiencing revulsion, he becomes dispassionate. Through dispassion the mind is liberated. With its deliverance he understands: ‘Assumption has been fully understood by me.”

Q:

“When the nutriment of contact/pressure is understood, the three feelings, pleasure, pain, neither-pleasure-nor-pain are understood.”

Nm: Exactly, because that’s where the pressure is, it’s where the feeling is. Fully understanding the nature of pressure, you have fully uprooted any resistance or welcoming towards respective feelings. In other words, you’re completely free from craving.

Q: Through understanding.

Nm: Yes, by understanding the pressure in regard to the currently enduring feeling, not by explaining it. But by understanding its nature, that will result in complete freedom from it.

Q: I can reflect on how I am subjected to feelings…

Nm: Yes, you could, but first, you need to feel the pressure. You can start these abstract questionings and self interrogations, but you first need to feel the pressure on account of whatever feeling is present there, because it’s there. Some pressure always has to be there, you can’t be in-between the pressures. No, there’s always something felt, which means there’s always something pressuring you, big or small, doesn’t matter, pressure is there. So, first, you need to stop acting out of that pressure habitually. Then allow the feeling to endure, then the phenomenon of pressure that manifests in regard to that, you can start interrogating its properties, and you can realise that in itself, the “pressure to act” is enough “in itself” it does not imply any action.

For example, an itch does not imply a scratch, you assume a scratch because you don’t want the itch. You assume the ‘act out of pressure to relieve the pressure’ because you don’t want the pressure. However, if you remove the gratuitous resistance to the pressure in itself, pressure is just the pressure, thus, it’s not pressuring you anymore. But for that, the mind needs to be developed in order to see that without giving in to that subtle attitude of either, “I want this” or “I don’t want this”. And the only way to develop the mind to see such subtlety, it needs to be able to endure the pressure sufficiently. You don’t need to find the right second or moment in-between pressure, so to catch your resistance before it happens. No. How do you become imperturbable? By practising not being perturbed, through enduring? You stop moving and the pressure to move will fade away because you’re not feeding it anymore. You also don’t practise immovability in regard to everything and nothing? No, in regard to the pressure that’s there on account of what you’re currently feeling, that’s where you practice endurance/khanti.

You need to find that level of presently enduring feeling, and don’t move there. Everything else is fine, everything else is second to it, everything else will fall in place, if you uproot the craving on the level where it matters.

Q:

"And how is the nutriment of mental intention to be regarded? Suppose there were a pit of glowing embers, deeper than a man’s height, full of embers that were neither flaming nor smoking, and a man were to come along — loving life, hating death, loving pleasure, resisting pain — and two strong men, having grabbed him by the arms, were to drag him to the pit of embers. To get far away would be that man’s intention, far away would be his wish, far away would be his aspiration. Why is that? Because he would realize, ‘If I fall into this pit of glowing embers, I will meet with death from that cause, or with death-like pain.’ In the same way, I tell you, is the nutriment of mental intention to be regarded. When the nutriment of mental intention is understood, the three forms of craving for sensual pleasures, craving for being, and craving for non-being are understood. When the three forms of craving are understood, I tell you, there is nothing further for a disciple of the noble ones to do.

Nm: What would be a practical example of mental intention?

Q: I want to go…

Nm: I want. That’s it. Wanting. I want this, I don’t want that. Now, you can think, “Oh, okay, I don’t want my wanting or I don’t want anything.”, but you can’t not want your wanting to be free of wanting because that’s now what you want. So you can’t just want your way out of your desire. The problem with the attitude of wanting is whether it pertains to the five cords of sensual pleasure, one way or the other, subtle or coarse. Is your wanting still pertaining to your gratuitous assumption of safety in this world? Is it still based on the gratuitous assumption of ownership, your own sense of self. Are those wants still revolving around those things? Because that is what needs to change.

That’s why the Buddha encourages us to replace the joys of sensual life with the joys of renunciate life, of a life that says no to sensuality. You can replace the miseries, the suffering of the sensual life with the suffering of the renunciate life because it’s better. The experiencing of joys and miseries for as long as you have the body, is not optional. But what’s optional is what joys and miseries will be experienced, whether they’re going to be pure or not, whether they’re going to be causing more attachment or not, whether they’re going to be causing more infatuation and lust or not. So replace the sensual ones with the renunciate ones and sustain that and there will be no more problems for you.

You can want anything else except the five cords sensual pleasures, for example. That’s it. Sustain that context and you will overcome lust or sensuality, because you’re not feeding it anymore through gratuitous sustaining of wanting it, i.e. valuing it.

The joys of seclusion are used to replace the joys of a household life. Pains of seclusion, pains of renunciation, replace the pains of a household life, which are far worse, far more burdening and create much further reaching consequences. Things you do on account of sensuality now, will have many consequences in lives to come, not just in this one. But pains of seclusion, renunciation pretty much end there, because there’s nothing done on account of it. No other people are affected by it, so it does not carry the same significance. And yet you used it to now replace all this other burden that would have otherwise have caused you so much more hassle.

That’s the mental wanting. It’s not like you cannot have it, but you should certainly make sure that none of it is rooted in the domain of the senses, in the domain of assumption of ownership. Is your wanting based on getting more pleasure, or a gratuitous sense of safety? Or is your wanting based on the practicality for living the holy life? Do you want enough food, enough shelter? Enough robes or clothes? Enough means to live by? Or is your wanting based on much more than that? So it’s about replacing the bad wanting with good wanting, and then sustaining the good wanting until you can completely disown even that.

Q: Why is it called nutriment?

Nm: Well, because your sense of self, your being, all of your assumptions are fed by it, dependent on it, sustained by it. Whether you want it or not, through acting on it, you’re feeding it. It’s a direct nutriment for bhava, for ego, for conceit, for ownership. It’s a vicious circle.

There are four types of nutriment and what’s in common with all those nutriments, is that they are nutriments for bhava, for your sense of self when you take them wrongly. So the one who is free from nutriment of food is free from bhava to that extent. An arahant doesn’t stop eating food, but eating food ceases to be the nutriment for his being because he has seen the danger in it. There is no wanting anymore, no desire, no lust in regard to the nutriment of food. Thus, it has ceased to be the nutriment for bhava, nutriment for his being and misconceptions. There is no more pressure either. Pressure was your wrong attitude which has been uprooted. As I said, “itch” is enough in itself, it does not require a scratch nor even imply it.

Q: But it’s still an itch

Nm: There is still an itch, but it does not pressure towards scratching it’s just an itch. So when you are not developed in regard to the itch, your mind cannot resist the thoughts, the delight, the pressure, the possibility of the scratch-to remove the itch. The itch in itself is self sufficient. It’s enough. In the itch there is just the itch. And if you start seeing it like that, you will not be pressured to scratch it. The pressure of scratching it will fade away.

As the Buddha said, phassa/pressure cannot pressure the groundless one. The one that has no ground for that pressure to land, no ownership, no delight, no lust in those thoughts of, “what if I only scratch it..”, none of that, he completely disowned them all, thus the thoughts of scratching do not pressure him anymore. The itch is there. The thoughts of scratching might be there but there is no pressure to scratch and then even the thoughts of scratching will fade away. And then again in the itch there’s just the itch, in the seen there’s just the seen, in the heard, just the heard and so on.

Q:

“And how is the nutriment of consciousness to be regarded? Suppose that, having arrested a thief, a criminal, they were to show him to the king: ‘This is a thief, a criminal for you, your majesty. Impose on him whatever punishment you like.’ So the king would say, ‘Go, men, and shoot him in the morning with a hundred spears.’ So they would shoot him in the morning with a hundred spears. Then the king would say at noon, ‘Men, how is that man?’ ‘Still alive, your majesty.’ So the king would say, ‘Go, men, and shoot him at noon with a hundred spears.’ So they would shoot him at noon with a hundred spears. Then the king would say in the evening, ‘Men, how is that man?’ ‘Still alive, your majesty.’ So the king would say, ‘Go, men, and shoot him in the evening with a hundred spears.’ So they would shoot him in the evening with a hundred spears. Now what do you think, monks: Would that man, being shot with three hundred spears a day, experience pain and distress from that cause?” “Even if he were to be shot with only one spear, lord, he would experience pain and distress from that cause, to say nothing of three hundred spears.” “In the same way, I tell you, monks, is the nutriment of consciousness to be regarded. When the nutriment of consciousness is understood, name and form are understood. When name and form are understood, I tell you, there is nothing further for a disciple of the noble ones to do.”

Nm: What’s the property of consciousness, practically speaking? What do all those things have in common? They are cognized. It’s the subtlest nutriment to understand. By understanding the nutriment food, you can be an anagami, but there will still be subtler forms of lust and aversion for “being”,”non-being” and remnants of conceit. Consciousness is the subtlest type of nutriment to understand because it’s on the level of the mere cognizing of things.

Are you cognizing those things with the implication of “for me”, “mine”, “I am”? Or are you cognizing those things as “not for me”, “not mine”, “not I am”? Just like the Buddha encouraged the noble disciples to regard everything.

Q: Why the simile of spears?

Nm: Any form of cognising already carries the conceit of “for me and mine”. So the only way to penetrate through that is to, again, just like the other similes, to regard it as the most horrible, perilous thing in the world, that must not be wanted, and then sustaining that context as the framework for any cognizing that arises until that cognizing is purified (of all conceivings), but you can’t do it on the level of cognizing it’s just too subtle. And your tool for doing it is cognizing, which is already corrupted by conceivings, by conceit.

What you can do is develop the framework of, “Okay, so any form of cognition, any situation I become self aware in, is like being struck with a spear, it’s a peril, a pain, the possibility of death”. So, what next? Nothing except sustaining that attitude and context, and there will be no more basis for passion and lust to endure and proliferate. It’s like the simile of “heating up a frying pan”, when the pan is really hot, even if you throw a lot of water on it, it will evaporate very quickly. That’s how you get rid of the conceit that’s affecting your cognition, by providing a hot pan for it to evaporate. The context is the hot pan of dispassion. The context should be, “This cognising is a spear that I might die as a result of”.

Ask yourself, “What is my current situation? What is my current state of mind? What is my current enduring feeling? What’s my current body posture?” All of that is a form of cognizing. So on that general level, that peripheral level, not on the particular level of, “I’m cognizing the table, I’m cognising the book, I’m cognising the phone,…” No, “I’m cognizing my current situation of such and such feeling enduring and I’m sitting here”, that’s the spear. The broadest context you can find is the spear, and that’s how you can then broaden even that context. Broaden in a sense of developing it further, so it becomes even more unsuitable for passion, for carelessness, for ownership. And if you find that unpleasant, it’s only unpleasant because of your ownership that is still there. If there is no ownership, it will not be unpleasant.

Same like when you put disinfecting alcohol on your skin. Unless your skin is broken and infected, it won’t hurt. It hurts only because there is a wound. But if you’re really unwise you will think, “It hurts because of alcohol, thus I won’t put the disinfectant on. I will just let the wound stay because I don’t want it to hurt.” When you develop the context and it hurts, it hurts because there is a wound which means if the wound heals, it will stop hurting without you needing to abandon the context.

Q:

“When the nutriment of consciousness is understood, name and form are understood. When name and form are understood, I tell you, there is nothing further for a disciple of the noble ones to do.”

Nm: If you fully developed the context of dispassion in regard to anything that can be cognized, there will be no more passion. In the cognised there will be just the cognised.